<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>KEJK | Thoughts</title>
        <link>https://kejk.tech/thoughts</link>
        <description>Thoughts on design, development and the intersection of the two</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 18 Jul 2021 19:04:13 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/nuxt-community/feed-module</generator>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why every designer should experience customer service]]></title>
            <link>https://kejk.tech/thoughts/why-every-designer-should-experience-customer-service</link>
            <guid>https://kejk.tech/thoughts/why-every-designer-should-experience-customer-service</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 18 Jul 2021 16:44:03 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[It's common when joining a new company to get thrown straight in at the deep end. Whilst not always …]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s common when joining a new company to get thrown straight in at the deep end. Whilst not always true, often the reason for your employment is because the team is currently understaffed and need additional bodies to help get things done or that there&rsquo;s a big new feature/product area that needs work and another colleague is needed to deliver that.</p><p>When this is the case, it&rsquo;s easy to overlook the value of ensuring that new employees experience a bit of frontline action. And in the case of my new role as a Product Designer at <a href="%22https%3A//www.moneyboxapp.com%22">Moneybox</a>, the experience I&rsquo;ve had so far is as a frontline customer service (CS) agent. My first two weeks are being spent alongside the wider CS team, learning about our customers&#39; pain points first-hand, as well as those moments of delight&mdash;such as someone being able to buy their first home thanks to our LISA&mdash;and providing them with world class customer service.</p><p>This is the first time as a designer that I&rsquo;ve not been designing something from day one, and honestly, it&rsquo;s the best feeling. Whilst I&rsquo;m itching to get started on my first design project, easing into a company who&rsquo;s product I&rsquo;ve used as a customer for the past 4 years by experiencing the CS role has been one of the most enjoyable onboarding experiences I&rsquo;ve had.</p><p>So far, I&rsquo;ve seen a trend; <em>things that come up via CS enquiries turn into new product features. Period</em>. Obviously this can&rsquo;t be true for everything we hear, including many customer feature requests, but for anything that is a clear customer issue that appears regularly, this is 100% the case. And this tells me something important; at Moneybox we care about our customer experience and it is embodied throughout the business.</p><p>The common requests that come up often (I can&rsquo;t talk specifics right now due to them being unreleased features) aren&rsquo;t things that we can&rsquo;t resolve already. Two of our new features are really straightforward to handle from our CS admin. But the truth of the matter is, a customer should <em>just be able to do it themselves</em>. So that&rsquo;s what we&rsquo;re doing. We&rsquo;re shipping features to make that true. And that embodies for me a culture of customer care and one of shipping necessary features often. It shows a connectedness across the business, from CS to Ops, Design to Development, Insight to Marketing. All of these departments are interconnected, and, woven throughout all of this is a desire to do the best for our customers. That&rsquo;s a place I want to be. Period.</p><h3>Key takeaways</h3><ol><li><strong>Customers do often know exactly what they want, but they won&rsquo;t always express it.</strong> Look for common pain points amongst the vast base of customers you or your colleagues speak to. Dig into the underlying need, don&rsquo;t take what they say at face value as a feature request.</li><li><strong>Customer Service is hard.</strong> Even with pre-written responses to the most common questions, it&rsquo;s a repetitive and demanding task to say the same things over and over with a positive attitude. It&rsquo;s also relentless. Take a moment to be grateful for your CS team and maybe have a coffee chat with one of them next week. Thank them for their efforts.</li><li><strong>Not doing your day job from day one is a really great way to start a new role.</strong> For all you managers out there, not trying to get a new employee to hit the ground running from day one is actually a really good thing. It&rsquo;ll help you to get the most out of them when they do actually start their role officially, and it&rsquo;ll help them to appreciate more of the wider business. Whilst intros to different departments are useful, they&rsquo;re a far cry from actually having to do the job for a bit.</li><li><strong>Secondments can be really valuable.</strong> Ask your employer for secondments into other areas of the business, even if just for a day, if you feel it&rsquo;ll enhance your role to do so. As a designer, spending time with CS, marketing/insights or development could have a significant positive impact on your day-to-day and allow you to see opportunities to improve your processes or push for a specific feature to be promoted in importance.</li><li><strong>Build a culture of connectedness.</strong> By encouraging departmental secondments, you ensure that you build a wider respect for different departments and connect your teams through action. A sales colleague may gain great value from spending time with marketing to understand how the product is sold direct to the consumer; a marketing colleague may find value in joining data science for a short time to gather insight about how they think about data; a data scientist may benefit from spending time with insight to see the true impact of the latest feature shipped. Not all secondments are created equal, but there&rsquo;s so much value that can be gained from time spent in another department.</li></ol><p>I&rsquo;m sure I&rsquo;ll have plenty more to say, but for now, these are my immediate raw thoughts on the process of being a CS for my first week. Ultimately, a secondment like this is nothing but a positive experience so if it&rsquo;s possible to do this in your company for new hires, make sure you do!</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>karl@kejk.tech (Karl Koch)</author>
            <enclosure url="https://imgix.cosmicjs.com/28abee30-e7e7-11eb-a375-6937647c8908-Why-every-designer-should-experience-customer-service2x.png" length="0" type="image/png"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What I've learnt over the past year]]></title>
            <link>https://kejk.tech/thoughts/what-ive-learnt-over-the-past-year</link>
            <guid>https://kejk.tech/thoughts/what-ive-learnt-over-the-past-year</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jun 2021 11:34:37 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Lessons I’ve learnt over the past year]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>2020 &mdash; 2021</h2><p>I didn&rsquo;t want to write a verbose blog post about the past year but the more I got to thinking, the more I felt it necessary to document (mostly for myself) the key lessons I&rsquo;ve learned from this past year. These lessons are not necessarily about Covid, they&rsquo;re about other factors that have impacted on my life too such as losing my father and from what my latest startup adventure has taught me.</p><p>Below are my observations, maybe you&rsquo;ll be able to learn something from these too.</p><h3>1. That deeply understanding what you&rsquo;re designing for by learning to build your idea is incredibly valuable</h3><p>This might feel obvious with a cursory glance, but it&rsquo;s true. Lots of people say it, and lots of people have varying opinions on what &lsquo;learning to build your idea&rsquo; truly is. In my mind, it&rsquo;s whatever it takes to realise your vision enough to make sense of it as a true end product, even if that&rsquo;s incredibly MVP.</p><p>I took this approach by building out Figma plugins to scratch an itch around weird interface quirks or missing features. I could have not bothered, or I could have asked someone else to build it, or even find the nearest alternative. But the reality is, I spent the time to learn to create them myself, in turn, I better understood how Figma works under the hood, and finally learned lots of valuable TypeScript along the way.</p><p>It taught me a lot about shipping products to customers, whether it&rsquo;s free or not, it matters. And it taught me a lot about taking on feedback and improving ideas, but without just doing <strong>everything</strong> someone asks for.</p><blockquote><p>Pithy takeaway: Learn to build things, no matter how small.</p></blockquote><h3>2. The value of building and having a robust design system is not to be ignored</h3><p>Design systems are complicated, they&rsquo;re time consuming to build well and there&rsquo;s still an enormous gap between the designed design system (in Figma, Sketch or another tool of choice) versus the coded component library (the name difference alone is irritating!).</p><p>However, taking the time to build out a robust system makes the world of difference in the long run. If you take the time to create flexible components, and think about their relationship to each other and their scalability, you&rsquo;ll start to reap the rewards pretty fast. If you can keep lesson 1 in mind too and actually try to create any of these in Vue, React, Swift or similar, then you&rsquo;ll also find limitations that allow you to rethink how you designed it in the first place. So you can go back and improve on its flexibility and scalability.</p><p>Robust systems also ensure consistency of your brand application across interfaces and other media. I saw a lot of worry previously about design systems being so good that a developer can build content without a design. Great! That should be the goal. If they can build views without Design mocking them up, Design can focus on defining the intention of the work, it&rsquo;s reason for being, the customer value, the stakeholder needs etc. Designing the intention, not designing the mock.</p><blockquote><p>Pithy takeaway: Design systems create room for more intentional work.</p></blockquote><h3>3. The importance of building strong design&mdash;dev relationships</h3><p>Learning how components are built, giving it a go yourself, that&rsquo;s all useful in ensuring a positive handover experience with Development/Engineering. But if they&rsquo;re not onboard with the design strategy and don&rsquo;t buy in to the use case of components then you&rsquo;re never going to build the best bond for the best end product.</p><p>Designers and Developers should be like Ham and Cheese, no matter what they go together. You should be in each other&rsquo;s pockets in a positive way, defining and scoping solutions from the outset, together. If you show willing by trying to prototype a component in real code or just showing that you&rsquo;ve considered limitations though good documentation, it&rsquo;ll go a long way. A great engineer will take the time to explain other limitations you may have missed and together you&rsquo;ll build something truly scalable and great.</p><blockquote><p>Pithy takeaway: Start building that relationship as early as you can. It makes the world of difference.</p></blockquote><h3>4. That business needs and product needs are often at odds with each other but that&rsquo;s okay, it&rsquo;s all about compromise</h3><p>Businesses have needs that can often vary from what the product really requires, for example, when fundraising a business will be focused on optics and future product vision, whereas during a period after fundraising, they&rsquo;ll likely focus more on growth.</p><p>It&rsquo;s common for these business needs to clash with product needs. Often VCs will turn down businesses by not ever saying no, and instead, by offering product feedback so they keep an open door in case you suddenly do find the traction they desire. When they do this, it&rsquo;s easy for stakeholders outside of the Product team to prioritise these seemingly &ldquo;important&rdquo; features. The reality is, these features are merely an easy out for the investor and will often lead to feature bloat in your product.</p><p>It&rsquo;s a tough line to walk, trying to appease VCs or business stakeholders is important, but it can be super hard to do this without straying from your product roadmap.</p><blockquote><p>Pithy takeaway: Compromise is key, but don&rsquo;t let business requirements derail your product roadmap.</p></blockquote><h3>5. That startups are hard, but a strong team and a true bond is enough to get you through it</h3><p>Never underestimate the power of building strong relationships. Working at startups, or any company for that matter, is incredibly difficult. But in reality, it&rsquo;s just business and businesses have their ups and downs. What gets you through is having strong relationships. Focus on building them and harnessing them to air out your concerns and worries along the way.</p><p>Having great friends outside of work is awesome, but they don&rsquo;t know what the day to day feels like. Having great colleagues internally, makes all of the difference. They understand the nuances of the businesses and are often times going through what you are. Don&rsquo;t be afraid to be vulnerable but avoid falling into hearsay and negativity.</p><blockquote><p>Pithy takeaway: Great relationships at work will see you through the toughest times.</p></blockquote><h3>6. That product managers are essential, if you give them the freedom to do their best work!</h3><p>A good Product Manager (PM) is like a good red wine; let them breathe for a little while and they&rsquo;ll only get better. I&rsquo;ve seen situations where Product Managers are essentially just task managers, writing Jira tickets and little more. This isn&rsquo;t good product management or good use of a Product Manager. They should write Jira tickets for definite, but not just that.</p><p>A good PM is given the freedom to do what they need to do at any time. To drive the team forwards and push for the best outcome for both the business and product team too. A good PM also works closely with design at the outset, working through user experience documentation and process; helping to define the pain points and intended happy paths, being part of the user research process, supporting the design documentation process and ensuring that there&rsquo;s a solid brief.</p><p>In some ways, in the outset of the design process, it should be hard to know which person is the designer and which is the PM, only when it comes to pursuing wireframes and detailed design processes should that split occur.</p><blockquote><p>Pithy takeaway: Product Managers are essential, but give them room to do their job!</p></blockquote><h3>7. That design, development and the intersection of the two are my lifeblood</h3><p>This is a personal one, but maybe one that is good to share. I&rsquo;ve learnt that caring about both design and development, understanding both of those processes and being confident in both are what excites me and keeps me motivated. Knowing that, writing it down and owning it, helps me to stay on course with my passions and guides my life choices accordingly.</p><blockquote><p>Pithy takeaway: Find your perfect fit. Lean into it. And never let it go.</p></blockquote><h3>8. To never underestimate the power of taking chances</h3><p>Like a Monopoly &lsquo;Chance&rsquo; card, taking a chance can be a risk that either has a reward or a negative consequence. Either way, every chance you take is a lesson learnt and in many ways is a chance to grow and evolve. Chances can either validate your decision making and improve your life or invalidate your decision making, change things and cause you to course correct. No matter which it is, you learn a lot by taking them.</p><p>Not all chances are created equal though. Gambling is chance (unless you&rsquo;ve got some mad skills) and is more often than not, likely to end badly. Changing careers is a chance that can equally either pay off or lead to a need to flip again. But whatever happens, own the chances you take and look at them from a longer-term perspective. You might find that what once felt like the worst thing that could ever happen, actually ended up changing your life for the better.</p><blockquote><p>Pithy takeaway: Over the long term, chances are what teach you the most.</p></blockquote><h3>9. To live every moment with intention</h3><p>Those who are close to me will know that I recently lost my father to his battle with cancer. It&rsquo;s been a very tough couple of months but practicing elements of buddhist and stoic ideologies has helped me to work through it all. Equally, channelling my inner &ldquo;Dad&rdquo; has helped a lot too.</p><p>My Dad was a true stoic, minimalist and intentional human. He believed in living in the present moment always and through his diagnosis and 6 and a half years of dealing with it, he never once complained or let it hold him back. Instead he made the most of every single moment he had on this planet. He explored parts of the country he&rsquo;d never seen before, spent time with the people he loved most, focused on restoring a forest nearby to where he lived and gave back to the planet more than he ever had before.</p><p>I&rsquo;m now focused on channelling him as much as I can to live my life with the most intention.</p><blockquote><p>Pithy takeaway: Live every moment with intention, but not like it&rsquo;s your last.</p></blockquote><h3>10. To be grateful for all that I have but not be complacent</h3><p>We&rsquo;ve been through a lot as a planet lately, but it&rsquo;s still very easy to live in a bubble of your own individual life and community (online or offline) without really appreciating what you have.</p><p>I&rsquo;ll keep this one short and sweet. But now more than ever, I have nothing but gratitude for my life, my family, my friends, and my career.</p><blockquote><p>Pithy takeaway: Love what and who you have in your life.</p></blockquote>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>karl@kejk.tech (Karl Koch)</author>
            <enclosure url="https://imgix.cosmicjs.com/ff5c95a0-c5f1-11eb-93bc-d7c81bee3189-D7882D40-C6C3-4DBA-ACA2-1CDDCE7EAEE2.png" length="0" type="image/png"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Spatial Design]]></title>
            <link>https://kejk.tech/thoughts/spatial-design</link>
            <guid>https://kejk.tech/thoughts/spatial-design</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jun 2021 22:05:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Product Design is a term we use broadly these days to define a designer who creates products.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Product Design is a term we use broadly these days to define a designer who creates products. This is a term that was often super unclear in my early days as I confused it with the role of an Industrial Designer. In reality, whether the product is digital
or physical, designing a product makes you, technically, a product designer.</p><p>We&rsquo;ve continued to expand the spectrum of what a Product Designer is and what their craft should be; from apps to websites, and virtual reality to audio-only, from physical products to the intangible. Product Design is the art of building something
from nothing, but I&rsquo;m seeing a shift in what that role should encompass, and I think we&rsquo;re going to have to hone our craft to include a new skill: Spatial Design.</p><p>Whether it be visual space or auditory space, being able to design for different spatial planes will be critical to the success of the next breed of designers as AR, VR, MR and audio-only platforms take off as the mediums of the future.</p><p>With the announcement of <a href="https://www.apple.com/uk/airtag/">Apple&rsquo;s AirTag</a>, playing with the delightful experience of finding a lost tag got me thinking carefully about what this design experience really was. The experience included
a physical product, a visual experience (including physics-rendered objects), a sense of spatial plane (vertical and horizontal direction), haptic feedback, and an auditory experience. That&rsquo;s a lot of things to cram into a single, small, $29 product.</p><p>The key to the success of the AirTag experience is in the team&rsquo;s sense of spatial planes when designing for it. Navigating the space of a room, understanding if the product is up or down from my current phone&rsquo;s placement, thinking about when
audio and haptic feedback play a key role in the finding experience. It&rsquo;s so many layers of complexity that lead to a cohesive and satisfying customer experience.</p><p>Comprehending that a single designer could ever create something like this is mind boggling, so its clear that this is a prime example of Apple&rsquo;s commitment to owning the entire stack and having individuals across the org playing a role. Say what
you will about the anti-trust element to this, as a customer it&rsquo;s a perfect experience, so there you have it.</p><p>No single designer should be expected to think of everything that leads to this product&rsquo;s success, or be capable of delivering upon it, but being able to have even one part of the vision for it and think about how all those world&rsquo;s collide
is something I think all designers would benefit from. Being able to think about Spatial Design when putting together a product in Figma that is purely two-dimensional will be critical to being a successful designer in the next few years. Spatial Design
doesn&rsquo;t have to mean that you design the spatial experience, but having understanding of the technology at play and the empathy to be in the shoes of the customer in that moment is crucial. And designing an experience that feels in concert with
the physical experience will be essential too.</p><p>This mindset follows on from my belief that all Product Designers should understand the core concepts of the development stack, even if they don&rsquo;t code [<a href="https://www.kejk.tech/thoughts/designing-in-code" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">1</a>, <a href="https://www.kejk.tech/thoughts/code-as-design" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">2</a>, <a href="https://www.kejk.tech/thoughts/thinking-in-design-code" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">3</a>]. Knowing how your idea is built is crucial to being able to design
optimally for it. With spatial design, it&rsquo;s exactly the same.</p><p>As we see the rise of AR, VR, MR and audio-only platforms, we&rsquo;ll see the need for designers to think about the spatial experience increase. There&rsquo;ll become plenty of specific jobs for AR Designer, Audio Designer, Spatial Designer and so on,
some of these even exist already if you look in the right places. But we&rsquo;ll also see the need for regular Product Designers to be thinking about the spatial experience alongside the host of other things they think about daily when designing products
for customers.</p><p>Customers will become increasingly invested in these spatial technologies, and as they do, designers will need to step up to the plate to deliver on those world class experiences. AirTag and Google Maps&#39; <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2019/8/8/20776247/google-maps-live-view-ar-walking-directions-ios-android-feature">AR directions</a> are just the start.</p><blockquote><p>Update, at WWDC21, Apple put together an <a href="https://developer.apple.com/wwdc21/10245" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">excellent video</a> on how to design for spatial interactions. I highly recommend checking it out!</p></blockquote>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>karl@kejk.tech (Karl Koch)</author>
            <enclosure url="https://imgix.cosmicjs.com/890faf80-b580-11eb-b5b6-fd115d17c053-Spatial-Design2x.png" length="0" type="image/png"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why you should reply to automated emails]]></title>
            <link>https://kejk.tech/thoughts/why-you-should-reply-to-automated-emails</link>
            <guid>https://kejk.tech/thoughts/why-you-should-reply-to-automated-emails</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 May 2021 13:22:30 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Picture this, it's an all too common scenario, you sign up to something to test it out and then forget…]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="-webkit-tap-highlight-color: transparent; -webkit-text-size-adjust: 100%;">Picture this, it&rsquo;s an all too common scenario, you sign up to something to test it out and then forget about it completely. Weeks later you come back to it and having forgotten you signed up to test it, you sign up again via different creds. Now, without realising it, you&rsquo;ve got two accounts.</span></p><p>Eventually you realise this and go back to delete one of those accounts. And, within minutes, you get an automated email about cancelling your account which asks for feedback on why.</p><p>This is exactly what happened with me and <a href="https://www.cosmicjs.com" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Cosmic</a>. I&rsquo;d signed up via Google originally, then forgot and signed up via GitHub only to decide that Google was what I&rsquo;d prefer to stick with (I&rsquo;d already put a load of data in by the time I realised). Now, as I&rsquo;d been using Cosmic for a while at this point, I was actually really bullish on it and sharing my feelings on Twitter and here. I&rsquo;d also written a <a href="https://www.cosmicjs.com/articles/how-to-post-to-a-cosmic-bucket-directly-from-the-drafts-app-d939e480-3bc8-11eb-a739-b574ca5054de" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">community article</a> about how I set up my publishing workflow via <a href="https://getdrafts.com" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Drafts</a>. I was well along my way to being an advocate, so I felt it necessary to reply to this automated email to explain that I, in-fact, was really into Cosmic and had shared so publicly.</p><p>I assumed it&rsquo;d go into a void of darkness like most replies to automated emails, but no, Tony (Cosmic CEO) replied and engaged me in good conversation about my use of Cosmic. I then got introduced to the Slack channel and built a bit more of a relationship before going back to my normal life.</p><p>After a month or so, Tony got back in touch and asked if I would be interested in figuring out a graphic for a <a href="https://www.cosmicjs.com/blog/jamstack-explained-in-5-minutes" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">blog post</a> being as I&rsquo;m a designer who uses Cosmic and thus understands how JAMstack works on a technical level. I obliged and, after a little back-and-forth, the visual went live and our professional relationship began.</p><p>Tony and I have a mutual love of interfaces void of clutter and noise, and so I couldn&rsquo;t resist mocking up some thoughts on where I felt Cosmic could go. Tony, quite frankly, loved it. So I worked on some more bits including a refresh to the above-the-fold main page design and&mdash;cut forward to a few months later&mdash;I&rsquo;m now proud to say that I&rsquo;m the <a href="https://www.cosmicjs.com/about" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Design Lead</a> at Cosmic, defining our design vision with Tony and building out the interfaces you&rsquo;ll be using day-to-day as a Cosmic user (when we ship our updates!).</p><p>So, what does this post ultimately tell you? Well, sometimes the simplest actions can lead to the most unexpected and exciting outcomes. I didn&rsquo;t need to feedback on why I &ldquo;chose to cancel Cosmic&rdquo; and I certainly didn&rsquo;t need to advocate online for Cosmic as a random customer. But when everything aligns, great things can happen.</p><p>Reply to those automated emails, you never know what might happen.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>karl@kejk.tech (Karl Koch)</author>
            <enclosure url="https://imgix.cosmicjs.com/96c97ac0-b580-11eb-b5b6-fd115d17c053-Why-you-should-reply-to-automated-emails2x.png" length="0" type="image/png"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The power of Cosmic]]></title>
            <link>https://kejk.tech/thoughts/the-power-of-cosmic</link>
            <guid>https://kejk.tech/thoughts/the-power-of-cosmic</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jun 2021 09:56:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[ Not too long ago I decided to set myself a challenge; create and add new content to my website via a CMS.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>Note: I work for Cosmic but this post is not directly affiliated with them and is my own set of opinions. I found Cosmic and starting using it before I worked with them, and actually its how I ended up working there!</p></blockquote><p>Not too long ago I decided to set myself a challenge; create and add new content to my website via a CMS.</p><p>So let&rsquo;s back it up. I&rsquo;m a designer by trade but I tend to get my feet wet in the development side too. If you&rsquo;ve read my posts previously or even looked on my site, you&rsquo;ll notice the distinct 50/50ish split of design and development
projects and/or posts. Being in control of the majority of the stack when it comes to projects I work on has proven super useful in terms of creative control and individual learning. But one thing I&rsquo;ve always found too abstract and difficult to
learn is backend development.</p><p>Frontend dev and design go hand in hand. I&rsquo;ve spoken vocally before about my belief that Designers should understand <a href="https://www.kejk.tech/thoughts/code-as-design">how their work is built</a> and should ideally be <a href="https://twitter.com/_kejk/status/1380866907377647618?s=21">comfortable</a> experimenting in that world themselves too.</p><p>Backend has always felt more complex to me, and APIs were a terrifying concept, so I went on the hunt for a headless CMS option to power my website and get my start in implementing API-driven updates to my website. I was looking through a host of different
options but specifically trying to get a good free tier that would enable me to power my website fully without having to pay until I was sure it was the right thing for me. This site makes me &pound;0, so keeping it as free as possible to run is ideal
(coincidentally this site only costs me about &pound;6 a month to run if you divide up the domain cost per year).</p><p>During my hunting I came across <a href="https://www.cosmicjs.com">Cosmic</a> and saw that it had a super generous free tier, one that could end up being viable for long-term use. Cosmic is a headless CMS that decouples your content from your frontend. By doing this, it meant I could create content &lsquo;buckets&rsquo; (to use Cosmic&rsquo;s nomenclature) to separate my content into different places and power different projects from it (more on why this is great later!).</p><p>Below I&rsquo;ve written five pieces of value a headless CMS can bring to your project or projects.</p><h2>1. Decouple your architecture</h2><p>By decoupling your backend from your frontend you can live in a world of a &ldquo;separation of concerns&rdquo;. This is important. By separating your content from your UI, you avoid putting all your eggs in one basket. I use <a href="https://www.nuxtjs.org">Nuxt</a> to build this website, so I could have used the <code>content</code> module to write markdown and post into my site. That leaves me reliant on Nuxt or another markdown-driven module, it couples me to the architecture. But by using Cosmic, I&rsquo;m able to write my markdown (like this post for example) in <a href="https://www.getdrafts.com">Drafts</a> and then <a href="https://www.cosmicjs.com/articles/how-to-post-to-a-cosmic-bucket-directly-from-the-drafts-app-d939e480-3bc8-11eb-a739-b574ca5054de">write a little script</a> to publish straight to my Cosmic bucket (and which now also runs a webhook in Vercel to republish my site and posts a draft into my <a href="https://www.buttondown.email">Buttondown</a> backend to create a new subscriber post). Now I&rsquo;m not reliant on Nuxt, so if a new framework shows up, or I decide to go back to vanilla JS again, I can still simply integrate all my content again.</p><h2>2. Separate your content into Projects or Buckets</h2><p>Your CMS may use different nomenclature for what Cosmic calls a Project or a Bucket, but essentially, each time you&rsquo;re working on a new project you don&rsquo;t need to spin up a brand new backend necessarily. By having a single Cosmic instance,
you can spin up as many Projects or Buckets as you like.</p><p>For this site I have a single Project with a single Bucket that contains all the necessary objects I need. I can then also target that Project but a separate Object to power my <a href="https://www.plugins.run">Plugins.run</a> site. I could also push that Object into its own Bucket if my needs grow.</p><p>But most importantly, it allowed me to spin up a new Project with some collaborators to build an exciting new <a href="https://twitter.com/_kejk/status/1387739445944782855?s=21">Figma plugin</a> project where all content is powered by Cosmic&rsquo;s backend&hellip; how awesome is that!</p><h2>3. Automate the upload of content</h2><p>On the topic of that Figma plugin, we have a lot of files to deal with from the outset (541 so far to be precise) which meant that we needed a way to get this content up quickly and easily. My collaborator <a href="https://neef.co/">Neef</a> put his skills to work and built a rad upload automation that meant we could easily post all of our files to Cosmic via the <code>add Object</code> endpoint by just dumping them in a folder locally and running <code>npm run upload:assets</code>. This stopped me
from manually doing all 541 (I&rsquo;d already done about 30 manually and that was horrible).</p><p>Without a headless CMS with a solid API, this would have been entirely manual and painful when each object has 5 points of metadata that need handling. It doesn&rsquo;t sound like a lot, but that&rsquo;s repetition over 2000 times, and this was just for
the first set of data.</p><h2>4. Power anything</h2><p>Following on from the above, by being able to power my website projects and also now a Figma plugin, it shows that a headless CMS can actually power anything. You could use one to power a website or app&rsquo;s content, power a plugin or integration or
even just as a repository of information you want to store.</p><p>My next goal is to start thinking about powering content in a native iOS app with my Cosmic CMS. Not sure on the project for this yet, but if you&rsquo;ve got ideas for something, send me an <a href="mailto:karl+appIdeaProject@kejk.tech">email</a>.</p><h2>5. Teach you about APIs</h2><p>Finally, learning how to implement your content via a headless CMS teaches you how APIs work and helps you to understand the relationship between content and UI and how this separation of concerns can improve, future-proof and power any project you&rsquo;re
working on.</p><p>Also, don&rsquo;t forget, you can go back and add a headless CMS solution to an older project. I did this with my pre-Nuxt website which used bare Vue (and thus didn&rsquo;t have the SEO benefits Nuxt brings) and it worked like a charm.</p><h2>Time to start something!</h2><p>Ultimately, a headless CMS offers freedom and power. If you&rsquo;re not sure whether one is the right fit for what you&rsquo;re doing, then I challenge you to try and find a way to make sense of it and do it. Everything you create in Cosmic is just a
JSON object that can be returned via the API. So if you&rsquo;re working on anything digital, you can use that JSON to do something. So I&rsquo;d say, anything is possible!</p><p>If you get stuck or want some advice, feel free to get in touch via the form below or head over to the <a href="https://www.cosmicjs.com/articles">Cosmic community</a> and see what people are building!</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>karl@kejk.tech (Karl Koch)</author>
            <enclosure url="https://imgix.cosmicjs.com/9fd7bf50-b580-11eb-b5b6-fd115d17c053-The-power-of-Cosmic2x.png" length="0" type="image/png"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Getting DRY with Figma plugins]]></title>
            <link>https://kejk.tech/thoughts/getting-dry-with-figma-plugins</link>
            <guid>https://kejk.tech/thoughts/getting-dry-with-figma-plugins</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 May 2021 13:23:03 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[There's a concept it DRY in development. It means Don't Repeat Yourself and is all about code reduct…]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There&rsquo;s a concept called DRY in development. It means Don&rsquo;t Repeat Yourself and is all about code reduction through declaring and reusing shared resources. Say for example that I have a simple conditional statement that checks for all the correct node types in a Figma plugin to determine if it can make adjustments. I could do the following to do it:</p><p><br></p><pre class="  language-javascript"><code class="  language-javascript"><span class="token keyword">if</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span>node<span class="token punctuation">.</span>type <span class="token operator">===</span> <span class="token string">&quot;FRAME&quot;</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>  </code>
<code class="  language-javascript">  <span class="token keyword">const</span> frame <span class="token operator">=</span> figma<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">createRectangle</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span>  </code>
<code class="  language-javascript">  frame<span class="token punctuation">.</span>width <span class="token operator">=</span> node<span class="token punctuation">.</span>width  </code>
<code class="  language-javascript">  frame<span class="token punctuation">.</span>height <span class="token operator">=</span> node<span class="token punctuation">.</span>height</code>

<code class="  language-javascript"><span class="token comment" spellcheck="true">// and so on</span></code>

}

<code class="  language-javascript"><span class="token keyword">if</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span>node<span class="token punctuation">.</span>type <span class="token operator">===</span> <span class="token string">&quot;GROUP&quot;</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>  </code>
<code class="  language-javascript">  <span class="token keyword">const</span> frame <span class="token operator">=</span> figma<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">createRectangle</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span>  </code>
<code class="  language-javascript">  frame<span class="token punctuation">.</span>width <span class="token operator">=</span> node<span class="token punctuation">.</span>width  </code>
<code class="  language-javascript">  frame<span class="token punctuation">.</span>height <span class="token operator">=</span> node<span class="token punctuation">.</span>height</code>

<code class="  language-javascript"><span class="token comment" spellcheck="true">// and so on</span></code>

}

<code class="  language-javascript"><span class="token keyword">if</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span>node<span class="token punctuation">.</span>type <span class="token operator">===</span> <span class="token string">&quot;ELLIPSE&quot;</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>  </code>
<code class="  language-javascript">  <span class="token keyword">const</span> frame <span class="token operator">=</span> figma<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">createRectangle</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span>  </code>
<code class="  language-javascript">  frame<span class="token punctuation">.</span>width <span class="token operator">=</span> node<span class="token punctuation">.</span>width  </code>
<code class="  language-javascript">  frame<span class="token punctuation">.</span>height <span class="token operator">=</span> node<span class="token punctuation">.</span>height</code>

<code class="  language-javascript"><span class="token comment" spellcheck="true">// and so on</span></code>

}</pre><p><br></p><p>But what I&rsquo;m doing there is redeclaring the same information multiple times, what a waste of compute power. So instead I can bundle these into one. It&rsquo;s difficult to use the <code class="  language-javascript"><span class="token operator">!==</span></code> declaration because so many things can need exclusion, so the best way is to use our friend <code class="  language-javascript"><span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">includes</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span></code>.</p><p><br></p><pre class="  language-javascript"><code class="  language-javascript"><span class="token keyword">const</span> nodeTypes <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token punctuation">[</span><span class="token string">&quot;FRAME&quot;</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span> <span class="token string">&quot;GROUP&quot;</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span> <span class="token string">&quot;ELLIPSE&quot;</span><span class="token punctuation">]</span> </code>
<code class="  language-javascript">  <span class="token keyword">if</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span>nodeTypes<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">includes</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>node<span class="token punctuation">.</span>type<span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>     </code>
<code class="  language-javascript">  <span class="token keyword">const</span> frame <span class="token operator">=</span> figma<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">createRectangle</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span>     </code>
<code class="  language-javascript">  frame<span class="token punctuation">.</span>width <span class="token operator">=</span> node<span class="token punctuation">.</span>width     </code>
<code class="  language-javascript">  frame<span class="token punctuation">.</span>height <span class="token operator">=</span> node<span class="token punctuation">.</span>height   </code>

<code class="  language-javascript"><span class="token comment" spellcheck="true">// and so on</span></code>

}

<code class="  language-javascript"><span class="token comment" spellcheck="true">// ...</span></code></pre><p><br></p><p>In design we can do a similar thing using atomic components, building up reusable assets as Lego blocks to avoid having to keep creating new assets. However, we can also take it a step further into the productivity side of design using Figma plugins.</p><p><br></p><h2>Figma Plugins, what&rsquo;s the deal?</h2><p>Well, you&rsquo;ve had a sneak peek at a bit of Figma plugin code above. Figma plugins use Typescript under the hood to allow you to create, modify and elevate your Figma project.</p><p>As you probably know, I&rsquo;m an evangelist for the &ldquo;Designers should Code&rdquo; philosophy, at least, I feel Designers should understand some code. And I&rsquo;ve taken that further to believe that knowing how to write enough Javascript to build
your own Figma plugins is a superpower all Designers should try to harness.</p><p>Figma plugins enable Designers to perform at optimum operational capacity without the burden of loads of admin overhead. Now there are tonnes of available plugins in the Figma Community but that doesn&rsquo;t mean you can find one to solve your problem, some issues are just too unique to your use case.</p><p>At HomeHero, we&rsquo;re using a bunch of custom Figma plugins that I&rsquo;ve written (including the ones I&rsquo;ve actually released)
to better maintain our files. I&rsquo;ll cover some of these below.</p><p>Ultimately, Figma plugins stop us from repeating ourselves with common admin tasks to clean up our files, they allow us to focus on designing the best experience instead of organising our contents.</p><p><br></p><h2>The &lsquo;Gist&rsquo; of how plugins work</h2><p>A couple of these Gists use the Scripter plugin to work as it has its own API to simplify some bits, grab it <a href="https://www.figma.com/community/plugin/757836922707087381/Scripter" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">here</a>. Of course, you can use the standard Figma API to perform any of this too, it just might be a little more verbose.<br><br></p><h3>HomeHero TextLint</h3><p>One of the first plugins I wrote for us was aimed at simplifying text linting. We have a bunch of phrases we write in our designs regularly thanks to our industry, and there are many times that we mistype them and this sometimes makes its way to the product
(oh dear!). To avoid that, I&rsquo;ve written a super simple linter that parses the document and updates all text characters that match my arrays. It&rsquo;s not the cleanest or best code, but it saves us a bunch of time.</p><p><br></p><pre class="  language-javascript"><code class="  language-javascript"><span class="token keyword">const</span> find <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token punctuation">[</span><span class="token string">&quot;Move in&quot;</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span> <span class="token string">&quot;move in&quot;</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span> <span class="token string">&quot;Homehero&quot;</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span> <span class="token string">&quot;wifi&quot;</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span> <span class="token string">&quot;Wifi&quot;</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span> <span class="token string">&quot;WiFi&quot;</span><span class="token punctuation">]</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span></code>
<code class="  language-javascript"><span class="token keyword">const</span> replace <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token punctuation">[</span><span class="token string">&quot;Move-in&quot;</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span> <span class="token string">&quot;move-in&quot;</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span> <span class="token string">&quot;HomeHero&quot;</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span> <span class="token string">&quot;Wi-Fi&quot;</span><span class="token punctuation">]</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span></code>

<code class="  language-javascript"><span class="token keyword">const</span> layers <span class="token operator">=</span> figma<span class="token punctuation">.</span>currentPage<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">findAll</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>node<span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token operator">&gt;</span> node<span class="token punctuation">.</span>type <span class="token operator">===</span> <span class="token string">&quot;TEXT&quot;</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span></code>
<code class="  language-javascript">figma<span class="token punctuation">.</span>currentPage<span class="token punctuation">.</span>selection <span class="token operator">=</span> layers<span class="token punctuation">;</span></code>
<code class="  language-javascript"><span class="token keyword">const</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span> selection <span class="token punctuation">}</span> <span class="token operator">=</span> figma<span class="token punctuation">.</span>currentPage<span class="token punctuation">;</span></code>

<code class="  language-javascript"><span class="token keyword">async</span> <span class="token keyword">function</span> <span class="token function">lintTextNodes</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">:</span> Promise <span class="token punctuation">{</span>    </code>
<code class="  language-javascript">  figma<span class="token punctuation">.</span>root<span class="token punctuation">.</span>children<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">flatMap</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>pageNode<span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token operator">&gt;</span>        </code>
<code class="  language-javascript">  pageNode<span class="token punctuation">.</span>selection<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">forEach</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token keyword">async</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span>node<span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token operator">&gt;</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>          </code>
<code class="  language-javascript">  <span class="token keyword">if</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span>layers<span class="token punctuation">.</span>length <span class="token operator">&gt;</span> <span class="token number">0</span> <span class="token operator">&amp;&amp;</span> node<span class="token punctuation">.</span>type <span class="token operator">===</span> <span class="token string">&quot;TEXT&quot;</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>              </code>
<code class="  language-javascript">    <span class="token keyword">await</span> figma<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">loadFontAsync</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>node<span class="token punctuation">.</span>fontName <span class="token keyword">as</span> FontName<span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>              </code>
<code class="  language-javascript">    node<span class="token punctuation">.</span>characters <span class="token operator">=</span> node<span class="token punctuation">.</span>characters<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">replaceAll</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>find<span class="token punctuation">[</span><span class="token number">0</span><span class="token punctuation">]</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span> replace<span class="token punctuation">[</span><span class="token number">0</span><span class="token punctuation">]</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>              </code>
<code class="  language-javascript">    node<span class="token punctuation">.</span>characters <span class="token operator">=</span> node<span class="token punctuation">.</span>characters<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">replaceAll</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>find<span class="token punctuation">[</span><span class="token number">1</span><span class="token punctuation">]</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span> replace<span class="token punctuation">[</span><span class="token number">1</span><span class="token punctuation">]</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>              </code>
<code class="  language-javascript">    node<span class="token punctuation">.</span>characters <span class="token operator">=</span> node<span class="token punctuation">.</span>characters<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">replaceAll</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>find<span class="token punctuation">[</span><span class="token number">2</span><span class="token punctuation">]</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span> replace<span class="token punctuation">[</span><span class="token number">2</span><span class="token punctuation">]</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>              </code>
<code class="  language-javascript">    node<span class="token punctuation">.</span>characters <span class="token operator">=</span> node<span class="token punctuation">.</span>characters<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">replaceAll</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>find<span class="token punctuation">[</span><span class="token number">3</span><span class="token punctuation">]</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span> replace<span class="token punctuation">[</span><span class="token number">3</span><span class="token punctuation">]</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>              </code>
<code class="  language-javascript">    node<span class="token punctuation">.</span>characters <span class="token operator">=</span> node<span class="token punctuation">.</span>characters<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">replaceAll</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>find<span class="token punctuation">[</span><span class="token number">4</span><span class="token punctuation">]</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span> replace<span class="token punctuation">[</span><span class="token number">3</span><span class="token punctuation">]</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>              </code>
<code class="  language-javascript">    node<span class="token punctuation">.</span>characters <span class="token operator">=</span> node<span class="token punctuation">.</span>characters<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">replaceAll</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>find<span class="token punctuation">[</span><span class="token number">5</span><span class="token punctuation">]</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span> replace<span class="token punctuation">[</span><span class="token number">3</span><span class="token punctuation">]</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>          </code>
<code class="  language-javascript">   <span class="token punctuation">}</span>         </code>
<code class="  language-javascript">  <span class="token keyword">return</span> Promise<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">resolve</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token string">&quot;Done!&quot;</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>       </code>
<code class="  language-javascript">  <span class="token punctuation">}</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span>  </code>
<code class="  language-javascript"> <span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>    </code>

<code class="  language-javascript"><span class="token keyword">if</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span>layers<span class="token punctuation">.</span>length <span class="token operator">===</span> <span class="token number">0</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>          </code>
<code class="  language-javascript">  <span class="token keyword">return</span> Promise<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">reject</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token string">&quot;No layers selected&quot;</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>  </code>
<code class="  language-javascript"><span class="token punctuation">}</span><span class="token punctuation">}</span>  </code>

<code class="  language-javascript"><span class="token function">lintTextNodes</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>  </code>
<code class="  language-javascript">figma<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">notify</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token string">&quot;All linted&quot;</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>  </code>
<code class="  language-javascript">figma<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">closePlugin</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span></code></pre><h3><br></h3><h3>HomeHero CropAll</h3><p>The second was a quick way to set all images to <code class="  language-javascript"><span class="token string">&quot;FILL&quot;</span></code> mode and apply a resize constraint on them. It&rsquo;s not full-proof, but it gets all your images to the same basic starting point. We needed to do this because we have a tonne of images we use for our Picks feature and they all need to be set to the same size to reduce bandwidth when served to the app.</p><p>When you have over 400 images, you want this!</p><p><br></p><pre class="  language-javascript"><code class="  language-javascript"><span class="token keyword">const</span> layers <span class="token operator">=</span> figma<span class="token punctuation">.</span>currentPage<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">findAll</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>isImage<span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span></code>
<code class="  language-javascript">figma<span class="token punctuation">.</span>currentPage<span class="token punctuation">.</span>selection <span class="token operator">=</span> layers</code>

<code class="  language-javascript"><span class="token keyword">for</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token keyword">let</span> shape <span class="token keyword">of</span> <span class="token keyword">await</span> <span class="token function">find</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token function">selection</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span> n <span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token operator">&gt;</span> <span class="token function">isImage</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>n<span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token operator">&amp;&amp;</span> n<span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span></code>
<code class="  language-javascript"><span class="token comment" spellcheck="true">// Update image paints to use &quot;FILL&quot; scale mode  </span></code>
<code class="  language-javascript">shape<span class="token punctuation">.</span>fills <span class="token operator">=</span> shape<span class="token punctuation">.</span>fills<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">map</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>p <span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token operator">&gt;</span>  <span class="token function">isImage</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>p<span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token operator">?</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span><span class="token operator">...</span>p<span class="token punctuation">,</span> scaleMode<span class="token punctuation">:</span> <span class="token string">&quot;FILL&quot;</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span><span class="token punctuation">}</span> <span class="token punctuation">:</span> p<span class="token punctuation">)</span>  </code>
<code class="  language-javascript">shape<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">resize</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token number">375</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span> <span class="token number">375</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">}</span></code></pre><h3><br></h3><h3>HomeHero Slide Export</h3><p>Finally, we work in Figma to create our investor slide decks and other slides to share our design progress or lunch and learns. It&rsquo;s great but it&rsquo;s annoying when you need to then turn these into an exported set of slides.</p><p>Luckily, we can use Figma plugins to apply some simple settings to make this happen and then export those Frames for others to use (you can even use my <a href="https://www.kejk.tech/lazy-pdf">Lazy PDF</a> app to compress it into a lossless PDF afterward).</p><p><br></p><pre class="  language-javascript"><code class="  language-javascript"><span class="token keyword">const</span> layers <span class="token operator">=</span> figma<span class="token punctuation">.</span>currentPage<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">findAll</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span> </code>
<code class="  language-javascript"><span class="token keyword">const</span> frames <span class="token operator">=</span> layers<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">filter</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>isFrame<span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>   </code>

<code class="  language-javascript"><span class="token keyword">async</span> <span class="token keyword">function</span> <span class="token function">renameFrames</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>     </code>
<code class="  language-javascript"> <span class="token keyword">let</span> items <span class="token operator">=</span> frames<span class="token punctuation">;</span> <span class="token keyword">if</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span>items<span class="token punctuation">.</span>length <span class="token operator">&gt;</span> <span class="token number">0</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>     </code>
<code class="  language-javascript"> <span class="token keyword">for</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token keyword">const</span> node <span class="token keyword">of</span> items<span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>       </code>
<code class="  language-javascript">  <span class="token keyword">if</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span>node<span class="token punctuation">.</span>type <span class="token operator">===</span> <span class="token string">&quot;FRAME&quot;</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>         </code>
<code class="  language-javascript">    node<span class="token punctuation">.</span>name <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>node<span class="token punctuation">.</span>name<span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">substr</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token number">0</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span><span class="token number">2</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token operator">!=</span> <span class="token string">&#39;Slide/&#39;</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token operator">?</span> node<span class="token punctuation">.</span>name <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token string">&quot;Slide&quot;</span> <span class="token operator">+</span> <span class="token string">&quot;/&quot;</span> <span class="token operator">+</span> node<span class="token punctuation">.</span>name <span class="token punctuation">:</span> node<span class="token punctuation">.</span>name<span class="token punctuation">;</span> <span class="token punctuation">}</span>       </code>
<code class="  language-javascript">  <span class="token punctuation">}</span>     </code>
<code class="  language-javascript"> <span class="token punctuation">}</span><span class="token punctuation">}</span>         </code>

<code class="  language-javascript"><span class="token function">renameFrames</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>     </code>

<code class="  language-javascript">figma<span class="token punctuation">.</span>currentPage<span class="token punctuation">.</span>selection <span class="token operator">=</span> layers<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">filter</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>n<span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token operator">&gt;</span> n<span class="token punctuation">.</span>name<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">startsWith</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token string">&quot;Slide/&quot;</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>     </code>
<code class="  language-javascript"><span class="token keyword">const</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span> selection <span class="token punctuation">}</span> <span class="token operator">=</span> figma<span class="token punctuation">.</span>currentPage<span class="token punctuation">;</span></code>

<code class="  language-javascript"><span class="token keyword">function</span> <span class="token function">hasValidSelection</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>nodes<span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span> <span class="token keyword">return</span> <span class="token operator">!</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token operator">!</span>nodes <span class="token operator">||</span> nodes<span class="token punctuation">.</span>length <span class="token operator">===</span> <span class="token number">0</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span> <span class="token punctuation">}</span> </code>
<code class="  language-javascript"><span class="token keyword">const</span> settings <span class="token operator">=</span> <span class="token punctuation">[</span> </code>
<code class="  language-javascript"><span class="token punctuation">{</span> format<span class="token punctuation">:</span> <span class="token string">&quot;PNG&quot;</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span> suffix<span class="token punctuation">:</span> <span class="token string">&quot;@1x&quot;</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span> constraint<span class="token punctuation">:</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span> type<span class="token punctuation">:</span> <span class="token string">&quot;SCALE&quot;</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span> value<span class="token punctuation">:</span> <span class="token number">1</span> <span class="token punctuation">}</span> <span class="token punctuation">}</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span> </code>
<code class="  language-javascript"><span class="token punctuation">{</span> format<span class="token punctuation">:</span> <span class="token string">&quot;PNG&quot;</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span> suffix<span class="token punctuation">:</span> <span class="token string">&quot;@2x&quot;</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span>constraint<span class="token punctuation">:</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span> type<span class="token punctuation">:</span> <span class="token string">&quot;SCALE&quot;</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span> value<span class="token punctuation">:</span> <span class="token number">2</span> <span class="token punctuation">}</span> <span class="token punctuation">}</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span> </code>
<code class="  language-javascript"><span class="token punctuation">{</span> format<span class="token punctuation">:</span> <span class="token string">&quot;PNG&quot;</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span> suffix<span class="token punctuation">:</span> <span class="token string">&quot;@3x&quot;</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span> constraint<span class="token punctuation">:</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span> type<span class="token punctuation">:</span> <span class="token string">&quot;SCALE&quot;</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span> value<span class="token punctuation">:</span> <span class="token number">3</span> <span class="token punctuation">}</span> <span class="token punctuation">}</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span> </code>
<code class="  language-javascript"><span class="token punctuation">{</span> format<span class="token punctuation">:</span> <span class="token string">&quot;SVG&quot;</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span> suffix<span class="token punctuation">:</span> <span class="token string">&quot;&quot;</span> <span class="token punctuation">}</span><span class="token punctuation">,</span><span class="token punctuation">]</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span> </code>

<code class="  language-javascript"><span class="token keyword">async</span> <span class="token keyword">function</span> <span class="token function">main</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>nodes<span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">:</span> Promise <span class="token punctuation">{</span>   </code>
<code class="  language-javascript">  <span class="token keyword">if</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token operator">!</span><span class="token function">hasValidSelection</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>nodes<span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token keyword">return</span> Promise<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">reject</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token string">&quot;No valid selection&quot;</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span>   </code>

<code class="  language-javascript">  <span class="token keyword">for</span> <span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token keyword">let</span> node <span class="token keyword">of</span> nodes<span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token punctuation">{</span>     </code>
<code class="  language-javascript">    node<span class="token punctuation">.</span>exportSettings <span class="token operator">=</span> settings<span class="token punctuation">;</span>   </code>
<code class="  language-javascript">  <span class="token punctuation">}</span>     </code>
<code class="  language-javascript">  </code>
<code class="  language-javascript"><span class="token keyword">return</span> Promise<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">resolve</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token string">&quot;Done!&quot;</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span> </code>
<code class="  language-javascript"><span class="token punctuation">}</span> </code>

<code class="  language-javascript"><span class="token function">main</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>selection<span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">then</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>res<span class="token punctuation">)</span> <span class="token operator">=</span><span class="token operator">&gt;</span> figma<span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">closePlugin</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>res<span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">;</span></code></pre><h2><br></h2><h2>Published plugins</h2><p>Beyond these, I&rsquo;ve written a bunch of small utility plugins to make designer life easier. You&rsquo;ll see them all on my <a href="https://www.plugins.run" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Plugins.run</a> site, but you can find them all <a href="https://www.figma.com/@_kejk">here</a> also.</p><h2>In the end, it&rsquo;s all about saving time</h2><p>Ultimately, we all want to save time and not do consistent, repetitive tasks each day. Figma plugins, and having the knowledge to write them, can be that solution for you. I can&rsquo;t count how many countless hours I&rsquo;ve saved myself by writing
the plugins I have and using plugins others have written too.</p><p>If you want to get started with Figma plugins, try out my <a href="https://gist.github.com/kemiljk" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Gists</a>, or, follow <a href="https://alcohollick.com/writing/figma-plugin-tutorial-1-6">this awesome tutorial</a> from <a href="https://twitter.com/DanHollick">Dan Hollick</a> who shares a lot of my feelings about designers and code.</p><p>If you do end up creating anything awesome for your team, please send me a note and share some Gists! I love seeing what people are up to and seeing how I can adapt and utilise what they&rsquo;ve done like I hope people do with my shares.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>karl@kejk.tech (Karl Koch)</author>
            <enclosure url="https://imgix.cosmicjs.com/aae0c270-b580-11eb-b5b6-fd115d17c053-Getting-DRY-with-Figma-plugins2x.png" length="0" type="image/png"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What a cult taught me about 'limiting beliefs']]></title>
            <link>https://kejk.tech/thoughts/what-a-cult-taught-me-about-limiting-beliefs</link>
            <guid>https://kejk.tech/thoughts/what-a-cult-taught-me-about-limiting-beliefs</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 May 2021 13:23:29 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[I've long been fascinated by cults from a psychological perspective. Knowing that particular individ…]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve long been fascinated by cults from a psychological perspective. Knowing that particular individuals can be so convinced by someone that a set of beliefs and ideals are true, they are willing to give up their previous life in search of this newfound one, both bewilders and intrigues me.</p><p>We could argue for ages about what constitutes a cult, people have varying opinions and I know where my beliefs lie, but that&rsquo;s beside the point.</p><p>The purpose of this is to think about the idea of &ldquo;limiting beliefs&rdquo;.</p><p>I first learnt about this concept when I was watching the documentary series <a href="https://m.imdb.com/title/tt10222764/">The Vow</a> about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NXIVM">NXIVM</a>,&nbsp;the celebrity-endorsed cult led by a narcissistic, self proclaimed genius, that did unspeakable things to convince women to brand themselves with his initial.</p><p>Interestingly though, like with most cults, it actually started out with positively challenging ideas and concepts that made a lot of sense. Limiting Beliefs feature in many self-help books, seminars and even many religions. They&rsquo;re the concept that we convince ourselves that we aren&rsquo;t capable of achieving something or being someone because we &ldquo;aren&rsquo;t good enough at it&rdquo; or &ldquo;don&rsquo;t live in the right city for that kind of job&rdquo; or &ldquo;can&rsquo;t do it because there isn&rsquo;t enough time in the day&rdquo;. Understanding and identifying our limiting beliefs and then&mdash;to use common cult nomenclature&mdash;reprogramming our minds to remove them is a core tenet of how NXIVM started and actually a positive thing I took away.</p><p>I&rsquo;ve long had limiting beliefs&mdash;which will be evident from previous articles&mdash;about my ability to be a designer based on my varied job history or that I&rsquo;m not really a frontend developer because I can&rsquo;t do everything from memory (despite knowing that most developers are this way).</p><p>Lately though, I&rsquo;ve been training myself out of this mindset. Using this concept of limiting beliefs to reprogram my own brain and I&rsquo;ve done this in the following five ways:</p><h2>Daily gratitude meditation</h2><p>I use a gratitude practice to remind myself daily that I&rsquo;m grateful to be employed as a designer, that I have a network of people who believe in my abilities as a designer and who trust me to do my job. It may seem silly, but that regular reminder to myself helps a lot.</p><h2>Regular practice</h2><p>I never stop practising my skills. Whether it&rsquo;s a paid job or an idea I want to try out, I practice often. I practice design skills, frontend coding skills and writing about the learnings. All of this helps me feel in control of my situation and feel like I know what I&rsquo;m doing.</p><p>I&rsquo;ve found that this personal website has become my experimentation ground. I&rsquo;m not the first person to do this, but it really does make for a safe place to experiment and learn.</p><h2>Being open and honest with people in my support network about my fears</h2><p>I&rsquo;m not afraid to talk to those around me about these worries. I speak to my manager often about my feelings of dissatisfaction with my work or output that day. I speak about my worries that I don&rsquo;t feel like I&rsquo;m really a designer. He reminds me regularly that I was hired as one for a reason and that if I was lacking in areas, he&rsquo;d tell me. Never underestimate the power of being told that.</p><p>I also often worry when it feels like what I&rsquo;ve produced is disliked by my team or could be a lot better. But then I&rsquo;m reminded that we&rsquo;re all stronger in different areas so some things take more time for one person to the next.</p><h2>Mentoring</h2><p>I&rsquo;ve been practicing being a mentor to junior designers seeking to push their skills forwards, especially within my team. I&rsquo;m trying to be a voice of experience, imparting the knowledge I&rsquo;ve gained about business, stakeholder management, how to manage design-developer handoff. All these things are things I sometimes take for granted but are less well<span style="-webkit-tap-highlight-color: transparent; -webkit-text-size-adjust: 100%;">&nbsp;known by junior designers.</span></p><h2>Writing about my worries in the open</h2><p>Finally, I write out in the open about my feelings more now. You&rsquo;ll notice these articles are often quite personal, and that&rsquo;s important. Sharing my experiences out in the open like this to the people who do choose to read it becomes kind of therapeutic. It&rsquo;s a chance for me to work through how I&rsquo;m feeling but also to share that it&rsquo;s normal to have doubts and worries.</p><p>Not all of these are right for everyone, and please let me know if you have other techniques that could be useful and I&rsquo;ll update this list.</p><p>Ultimately though, in this new year, rather than reflecting on the previous year or saying what will be new this time around, I&rsquo;d rather share some insight from my own personal journey through my limiting beliefs and leave you with this:</p><blockquote><p>You should never feel like you have no limiting beliefs, but you should always fight to overcome them. The moment you stop being limited or you stop fighting, you&rsquo;ve become too comfortable and need to find your next challenge.</p></blockquote>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>karl@kejk.tech (Karl Koch)</author>
            <enclosure url="https://imgix.cosmicjs.com/b73dbcd0-b580-11eb-b5b6-fd115d17c053-What-a-cult-taught-me-about-limiting-beliefs2x.png" length="0" type="image/png"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How music, design and code are all the same]]></title>
            <link>https://kejk.tech/thoughts/how-music-design-and-development-are-all-the-same</link>
            <guid>https://kejk.tech/thoughts/how-music-design-and-development-are-all-the-same</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 May 2021 13:23:56 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[I wouldn't say I believe creativity is a gift we're born with. I don't believe my abilities are.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I wouldn&rsquo;t say I believe creativity is a gift we&rsquo;re born with. I don&rsquo;t believe my abilities are. But what I think I do have is a natural tendency towards patterns.</p><p>The more I&rsquo;ve look introspectively at myself lately, the more I&rsquo;ve come to see that the &ldquo;red thread&rdquo; through the three things I&rsquo;m best at and enjoy, is patterns.</p><p>The idea that music, design and development are all ultimately the same at their core has occurred to me many times, most recently when I was listening to the radio. The reason? The specific patterns (n&eacute;: formula) pop songs all stick to.</p><h2>Pop songs</h2><p>There&rsquo;s only so many pop songs in the world, and they&rsquo;ve already all been written, rewritten and written again. The people who write them are aware they&rsquo;re not new, they want that to be true, because there&rsquo;s a set of sequences
that work and work well. Why diverge from them? People like familiarity, it&rsquo;s human nature.</p><p>Design and development for that matter are the same. Design patterns are critical for making something pleasing to the eye. Early in most creative classes you&rsquo;ll learn about the oft touted &ldquo;Golden Ratio&rdquo;. This particular number (1.618)
when used as a compositional spacing rule, leads to the most pleasing results mathematically which happen to be aesthetically pleasing too. Why? Pattern recognition.</p><h2>Understanding this article</h2><p>Littered throughout this article are links to other articles and websites. This is deliberate and not due to laziness. Lots of clever people have written great pieces on the things I&rsquo;m talking about here, so my goal is to collate a series of these
thoughts into an abstract of sorts. Think of this like a meta-analysis of these other thoughts.</p><h3>The golden ratio and nature</h3><p>If we break down nature&rsquo;s patterns, we can find the <a href="https://www.treehugger.com/how-golden-ratio-manifests-nature-4869736">golden ratio everywhere</a>. Its in the snowflakes that fall in winter, the leaves that grow on trees, the scales
on a fish, or the way a forest grows.</p><p>There&rsquo;s a reason it exists everywhere, its because it creates aesthetically pleasing results. Nature is an incredible thing and the results are beautiful. If we use those patterns ourselves in music, design and development, we get beautiful results too.</p><p>So lets break down some of the similarities between the mediums by picking some core terminology and finding some examples.</p><h3>The rule of thirds</h3><p>In photography there&rsquo;s the concept of the <a href="https://photographylife.com/the-rule-of-thirds">Rule of Thirds</a>, where you aim to create a pleasing proportion to your image by aligning the subject to different thirds within their containing
frame. Just like all creative rules though, sometimes breaking them leads to more intriguing results, and this is very common when using the rule of thirds.</p><p>In design we can use the rule of thirds when <a href="https://designwebkit.com/web-design/rule-of-thirds-web-design/">laying out a website or app</a>, or when composing an article. It can often help us to pair the notion of the rule of thirds with grid
layouts. Pairing the two can lead to interesting and dynamic layouts whilst maintaining logic and legibility.</p><p>In music we can use the rule of thirds in many ways, mostly it&rsquo;s a logical way to think about breaking up a composition. Take a traditional <a href="https://www.teenstarcompetition.co.uk/advice/how-to-write-a-pop-song">pop song</a>: intro, verse,
chorus, verse, chorus, bridge, middle eight, chorus. Here, to create the catchy moment people always look forward to in songs, often the end of a pop song leverages the idea of using a bridge, then a middle eight (which is often a stripped down version
of the same chorus melody) and then ending with a big final chorus. This use of a triad is one of the major reasons pop songs feel so catchy, they&rsquo;re predictable.</p><p>Design and development layouts should also maintain predictability, this predictability is what makes a design usable and pleasing to look at.</p><h3>Grids</h3><p>Depending on who you are, <a href="https://www.interaction-design.org/literature/article/the-grid-system-building-a-solid-design-layout">grid systems</a> are either a blessing or a curse. If we think about them the same as the rule of thirds then we&rsquo;re on the right path. Grids can be used as a definitive approach to layout or be used as an element we purposely break to provide a unique aesthetic approach. Either one is acceptable, it&rsquo;s just up to you and your layout intention.</p><p>In music we have a similar principle to grids in instrumental composition. Choosing how to &ldquo;<a href="https://youtu.be/S8fZ62FrquQ">arrange</a>&rdquo; instruments is vital to the feel of a song. We can choose to have all instruments playing at once,
or start with just one and build it up. Similar to grids, we can use different structural layouts to create the final song, and those different structural layouts dramatically impact the feel of the piece.</p><h3>Colour theory and white space</h3><p><a href="https://99designs.co.uk/blog/tips/the-7-step-guide-to-understanding-color-theory/">Colour theory</a>, surely there isn&rsquo;t a corollary to anything in music here? Well, not so fast there champ. We can make a comparison here to the idea of
harmony. Colour theory is the idea that selecting colours that are opposites on the colour wheel leads to a pleasing compositional choice as they balance each other out. Why is that? It&rsquo;s because they contain the opposite values, this fills out
the colour spectrum to its whole.</p><p>In music we have a similar thing. Have you ever wondered why the majority of songs contain drums, bass, guitars/synths and vocals, for example? It&rsquo;s not by chance, its because these instruments fill the entire audible spectrum humans can perceive.
There are only so many frequencies that we can hear, by filling space in each of them we can create audible balance.</p><p>Then, in both cases, we can play on this idea by breaking these rules at certain moments. Think of the famous &ldquo;<a href="https://dj.dancecult.net/index.php/dancecult/article/download/451/457">bass drop</a>&rdquo; in dance music, or dropping to one
guitar before all coming back in, or even moments of complete silence. These are tactics musicians use to create space in the composition and therefore generate the drama and anticipation of when it kicks back in.</p><p>In design we do this too by using <a href="https://blog.prototypr.io/importance-of-white-space-in-design-5a40c0e65bfd">white space</a> to create a void between the content and colours, creating impact when we drop back in to the palette. We can also do this by dropping to a single colour for a moment and then bringing back the contrast of our secondary opposite colour to fill the visual out.</p><h3>Rhythm</h3><p>You can keep all your instruments together following the same rhythm and harmony. This is pleasing to the ear in the fact that it feels together and its easy to nod your head to. Alternatively, you can mix different rhythms or harmony&rsquo;s to produce interesting results. In music we have what&rsquo;s known as a <a href="https://mathdrumming.com/polyrhythms/">polyrhythm</a>. This is a rhythmic device where an instrument maintains a rhythm that falls outside of the time signature of the composition
but, thanks to some maths, falls back into time within a later phrase of the other instruments rhythm.</p><p>Similarly, in design we can use rhythm and harmony when we think about a layout. When laying out <a href="https://www.jeroenseynhaeve.com/pythagoras-and-vertical-rhythm-in-typography/">typography</a>, rhythm and harmony are words that often come up. That&rsquo;s
because what makes typography often feel pleasing to look at and read is the consistency by which the elements are laid out. If we break this typographic rhythm then it can either have pleasing results (such as for a poster design) or feel unbalanced
and terrible because of a lack of visual consistency.</p><h3>Time signatures and pacing</h3><p>Much like rhythm, we can use other mathematical devices to play with our composition. Pacing is key to this, it allows us to think about how fast and slow the entire song should be, but also the speed of each section. Is it full time, is it half time.
Playing with the pacing is another device we can use to change the feel between sections and drive impact.</p><p>If you ever listen to music I&rsquo;ve written for Echoes, we play on this idea quite often by leveraging the drama of half time. We love dropping to a final half time ending on a lot of our songs. We do this deliberately because it provides the drama
and release that the build up to the moment expects.</p><p>In design we can do this too by building up different layers of composition. By having sections of your design filled with an image, text and buttons, then dropping to a section with just a single centre-aligned paragraph, then an image, and then back
into a full section with all elements. Doing this creates visual drama and dynamism. It also helps to draw attention to the right things at the right time.</p><p>Equally, we can play with <a href="https://www.musicnotes.com/now/tips/a-complete-guide-to-time-signatures-in-music/">time signatures</a> which allow us to create different dynamic rhythms to create more unique feels. Jazz is full of this, but so is a lot of modern metal music.</p><p>Rap and hip hop use a very common layering of 4/4 backing rhythms and then rapping in <a href="https://hellomusictheory.com/learn/triplets/">triplets</a> over the top. This is what makes the vocals feel like they&rsquo;re running at a faster pace than the lyrics and feel really fluid. You can count 1, 2, 3 in fast succession over the 4 measures to hear how it works.</p><p>In design we can use this idea visually by using contrasting grids on top of each other. Think how it would look to have your type laid out evenly over a 4 block grid but spaced as if it was a 3 block grid. It would create interest by adding additional
white space between the words, creating a more intriguing rhythm.</p><h3>Combining our principles</h3><p>In the below example, the navigation bar at the top and the two circular graphics fall on the 4x4 grid whereas the title text sits on a 3x4 grid. Just like triplets fall inside a 4/4 rhythm, different grids can work in harmony to create more interesting
layouts. This combines our principles of grids, rhythm, pacing, colour theory, white space and time signatures. Almost all of them!</p><figure><img src="https://res.cloudinary.com/kejk/image/upload/v1608475542/B49E0789-1597-44A0-B7D1-2668F5ED8CF0_nhp92f.png" alt="3x4 text on a 4x4 layout" class="rounded-lg fr-fic fr-dii"><figcaption>3x4 text on a 4x4 layout</figcaption><p><br><span style="-webkit-tap-highlight-color: transparent; -webkit-text-size-adjust: 100%;">You&rsquo;ll likely find that you often combine many of these principles, and if you&rsquo;ve been designing or developing projects for a while then you may find you naturally use a lot of these techniques. Ultimately, this post aimed to show how similar all of these skills really are and how a common thread of pattern-based logic can lead to aesthetically pleasing results.</span></p></figure>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>karl@kejk.tech (Karl Koch)</author>
            <enclosure url="https://imgix.cosmicjs.com/c68fdb50-b580-11eb-b5b6-fd115d17c053-How-music-design-and-code-are-all-the-same2x.png" length="0" type="image/png"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Thinking in design-code]]></title>
            <link>https://kejk.tech/thoughts/thinking-in-design-code</link>
            <guid>https://kejk.tech/thoughts/thinking-in-design-code</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 May 2021 13:25:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[My personal approach on how to think about code from a design perspective and how to implement those changes.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve said before that I&rsquo;ve built this personal site three times so far, and in all three cases it was without any design file in site. Now, as a designer this might seem like a really weird approach to building out something that requires
design, but I designed it in code. Hear me out.</p><p>If you&rsquo;ve read any of my other Thoughts before then you&rsquo;ll be familiar with my concept of <a href="https://www.kejk.tech/thoughts/code-as-design">Code as Design</a> but for this piece I want to take it a little bit further.</p><h3>The premise</h3><p>So to understand why I took this approach&mdash;and for those who haven&rsquo;t read my previous articles&mdash;you&rsquo;ll need to know that I am a designer but I&rsquo;ve had a varied background that grew from learning the basics of HTML and CSS in
the early 2000&rsquo;s. So really, I actually learnt the principles of web design through the lens of code.</p><p>So below I&rsquo;m going to outline some practical steps of how to relate code and design. This list won&rsquo;t be exhaustive or complete necessarily (although I may come back and add to it) but it should match pretty well.</p><p>Some caveats:</p><ul><li>All references to design tools will be through the use of Figma&rsquo;s terminology. This is for three reasons:<ol><li>It&rsquo;s a pretty ubiquitous design tool now, used by many</li><li>It&rsquo;s what I use day to day for my job, so I know it very well</li><li>Most of Figma&rsquo;s terminology for tools map fairly synonymously with code (particularly the new flex box-inspired auto layout</li></ol></li><li>This is how I think of code and design being linked, it doesn&rsquo;t mean that it&rsquo;s the only way to think about it</li><li>I&rsquo;ll do my best to explain any concepts in as much detail as I can, but I can&rsquo;t promise it&rsquo;s exact</li><li>This entire piece revolves around the principle of a web project build, you can of course map these same ideas to mobile builds in SwiftUI for example, the exact names will vary slightly (a div for example is more likely to be an Stack or even a Struct
depending on how you build your projects, and grids are called LazyVGrid/LazyHGrid respectively)</li></ul><h3>Projects == Folders</h3><p>Where better to start than projects. In Figma, a &ldquo;Project&rdquo; is a folder that contains a series of files that you work on. You can have one, several or many. In Code, we use folders (just a regular old computer folder) and inside those folders
we keep files which contain our code. Like with a Figma project, a folder can contain one, several or many files.</p><p>If you work in modern Javascript-based frameworks, you&rsquo;ll likely have a whole bunch of files. If you&rsquo;re just keeping it minimal you may only use a single HTML file.</p><h3>Files == Files</h3><p>Well this ones easier right? Each Figma file inside your project is essentially synonymous with the file structure of a development project. You can create multiple files within a project and link them all together with Figma&rsquo;s Shared Libraries feature.</p><p>For most development projects, especially those that utilise one of the Javascript frameworks, there will be a bunch of files that all play together nicely (hopefully) to build your site. Figma projects are no different if you take full advantage of the
Shared Libraries in Figma (and you should). Decentralising files is a key fundamental in modern development and allows for greater reusability and manageability of your code. Thinking of design files like this too will not only make your files more manageable
but will also create a wider synergy to your development project when it progresses.</p><h3>Frames == Divs</h3><p>Frames in Figma are your canvases. Frames are where you &ldquo;paint&rdquo; the interface of the product or thing you&rsquo;re designing, and in development the notion of &ldquo;painting&rdquo; is true too.</p><blockquote><p>Sidenote: You may see the phrase &ldquo;Time to first paint&rdquo; if you ever do a Google Lighthouse review of your site, this is Google telling you the time it takes for your site to load the initial interface and allow first interaction. If it&rsquo;s
slow, you&rsquo;ll score low for SEO and with Javascript-based Single Page Apps this can be a problem, so keep an eye on it.</p></blockquote><p>Just like in Figma, Divs act as a container for your code and you can stack as many Divs inside each other as you need (just like Frames). By doing this, you build up a structure for your page. This is where it can start to take life. It&rsquo;s important
to stay focused on building out the core Div structure before getting into the details. Use quick &ldquo;styles&rdquo; on your Divs to create visual separation&mdash;even if it looks garish&mdash;such as `class=&ldquo;border-2 border-black bg-red-500&rdquo;.
I&rsquo;d use primary colours to separate the independent elements and stop you from nitpicking the details.</p><p><a href="https://gist.github.com/kemiljk/67631887f63e7b3b047364ef5df764f4" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">This Gist</a> is an example of building up the basic structure of my home page container utilising the TailwindCSS library.</p><h3>Auto Layout == Flexbox and Grid</h3><p>In the above code you&rsquo;ll see some examples of &lsquo;flex&rsquo;, &lsquo;flex-row&rsquo; and &lsquo;grid&rsquo;. These are all layout mechanisms that help to structure the page content in a more fluid and dynamic way. They&rsquo;re particularly important for when you want to create responsive layouts, such as having a 1 x 4 grid turn from a single row into a single column between desktop and mobile. This is exactly what happens in that first grid line <code class="  language-html">&lt;divclass=&quot;grid xs:grid-cols-1 sm:grid-cols-2 md:grid-cols-4 gap-4&quot;&gt;</code>.
At the smallest breakpoint (phone) it&rsquo;s a single column, at the next breakpoint (tablet portrait) it&rsquo;s two, and then at the next and up (tablet landscape or desktop) it turns into a four-column row. At each stage I implement a 4-point gap
to separate the elements.</p><p>If you look at the new Figma Auto Layout and Constraints controls, you&rsquo;ll see a lot of familiarity with these flex principles too.</p><figure><img src="https://res.cloudinary.com/kejk/image/upload/v1608155456/7BDEFC0F-89CB-4CA5-B93C-1B2A55646CEE_ewz2ye.jpg" alt="An image of the Flexbox-like layout" class="w-screen md:max-w-xl rounded-lg fr-fic fr-dii"><figcaption>An image of the Flexbox-like layout<br><br></figcaption></figure><p>In the above we can see the flex direction (the down and right arrow) the spacing between elements (in grid, this is the grid-space-row or grid-space-col or in TailwindCSS, gap-{n}), the overall padding (here it&rsquo;s 16px on every side) and the alignment
(in our example this is align-center, justify-center).</p><p>You can also set resizing constraints. This defines how the object behaves when resized. We can choose between &ldquo;Hug contents&rdquo;&mdash;where the frame itself (i.e. the Div) is perfectly connected to the width of the objects inside and maintains
the padding and wrapping&mdash;or &ldquo;Fixed width&rdquo; where the the frame width never changes regardless of changes to the internal components. The same rules can be applied to the height property.</p><p>Below is how this looks in practice. Hug Contents is above and Fixed Width below. Notice that because I have the align-center and justify-center properties in place, the objects stay perfectly in the middle with fixed width.</p><figure><img src="https://res.cloudinary.com/kejk/image/upload/v1608155455/F93AD77E-441A-458B-9D80-039C5B97F194_o9tw8w.png" alt="Image example of the different container options on Figma" class="w-screen md:max-w-xl rounded-lg fr-fic fr-dii"><figcaption>Image example of the different container options on Figma<br><br></figcaption></figure><h3>Layer naming == ID or Class</h3><p>Now let&rsquo;s talk about layers and naming. I know, I know, it&rsquo;s totally boring and it&rsquo;s fine to have &lsquo;Rectangle 33201&rsquo; or &lsquo;Frame 1000010&rsquo; on your projects if the actual designs look cool. I&rsquo;ve done it many
times too. But there is a really valid reason to think more carefully about layer naming, implementation in code.</p><p>If you can handover a file that&rsquo;s name logically from a layering perspective (especially if you&rsquo;ve taken all the above steps too) then you&rsquo;ll find your Engineer(s) have a much easier time implementing the code as they can use it as their
file architecture or map.</p><p>Groups should be given a name that characterises the contents. This is what can relate directly to an &lsquo;ID&rsquo; property or a &lsquo;Class&rsquo;. IDs by their very nature must be unique. In real life you can only have a single form of ID from
a single source, the same applies to code. You should use an ID once in your code and not again. If you find yourself repeating them then you should swap these to become classes instead.</p><p>An ID gives your particular Div or object a unique identifier which determines what makes it different. You could name a Nav Div, for example, <code class="  language-text">NAV</code> as you should only have one implementation of your core Navigation and reuse that component everywhere (more on this later). If that is true, ID it as <code class="  language-text">NAV</code> and apply the relevant classes.</p><p>Notice the use of uppercase. Everyone has different practices, but one I think is particularly useful is to use UPPERCASE words to represent IDs and kebab-case for classes. But really you can do what you want. The reason for a difference? Scanability.</p><h3>Styles == Classes</h3><p>Now, in Figma, if you find yourself reusing a particular style everywhere then you&rsquo;ve probably decided (at least I hope so) to create a Figma Style from it. Doing this allows you to create local Text Styles, Color Styles and Effect Styles for a
document. That way, repetition is more easy to do and consistency is more likely to be had.</p><p>In code we do this too, they&rsquo;re known as classes. Depending on whether you&rsquo;re using a CSS library (like <a href="https://tailwindcss.com/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">TailwindCSS</a>) or not will likely determine your approach to classes. Tailwind uses what are known as &lsquo;<a href="https://adamwathan.me/css-utility-classes-and-separation-of-concerns/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Utility Classes</a>&rsquo;, essentially breaking classes up into atomic parts (see: <a href="http://atomicdesign.bradfrost.com/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Atomic Design</a>). What this means in practice is, like in my example earlier, there&rsquo;s lots of bitty classes used to
build up a base idea.</p><p>Just look at this button: <code class="  language-html">&lt;button type=&quot;button&quot;class=&quot;flex flex-row w-full justify-center text-center font-medium btn btn-primary rounded-xl px-6 py-3 bg-blue-400 text-white hover:bg-blue-500 focus:outline-none focus:shadow-outline transition duration-500 ease&quot;&gt;Button 1<span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;/</span>button</span><span class="token punctuation">&gt;</span></span></code></p><p>That&rsquo;s a big ol&#39; lot of classes to get the button behaving how I want. But equally, it behaves how I want. I&rsquo;ve have complete control in the place I&rsquo;m creating the button, instead of relying on styling in a separate CSS file. And, once you learn the notation style, it actually gets pretty fast to write (see: <a href="https://brianlovin.com/overthought/tailwind-css-first-impressions" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Brian Lovin on migrating to TailwindCSS</a>).</p><p>The next logical step, of course, is to reduce the amount you do this. And you do this, just like in Figma, through making reusable elements called Components.</p><h3>Components == Components</h3><p>Now on to the final piece of the puzzle. You&rsquo;ve written a bunch of stuff, but you find yourself copying and pasting it all the time. Doesn&rsquo;t it seem silly to do that? Couldn&rsquo;t it be easier?</p><p>This is where component based design and development comes in. Breaking things up into reusable chunks makes it easier to manage a big build and increases consistency. The beauty of Components too, is that you can decide how atomic you want to make them.
Atomic Design (mentioned earlier) is the extreme end of the spectrum, but if you&rsquo;re already using TailwindCSS then you&rsquo;ve already got a bunch of atomic elements to play with.</p><p>If I dissect my site, I have:</p><ul><li>Four core unique pages</li><li>One subpage (for blog posts)</li><li>Fourteen components</li></ul><p>I could be much more atomic with my components. If it was a commercial product, I would be, but the reality is that I don&rsquo;t need to be that strict about it. I&rsquo;m building it to my needs, just like I would a personal Figma file. The most important
part of creating a component of anything is thinking about who&rsquo;s going to use it. Think of your website the same way you think of a Figma Design System. If you created icons with their labels as components, do the same, they&rsquo;ll be easier to
swap out in a conditional statement. If you created different card component types, do the same, again you can use conditionals to control data differences.</p><h3>Conclusion</h3><p>If you&rsquo;re working with engineers on a project, talk it through with them. Ask them how they&rsquo;re planning to execute at a code level and build your project to match. If they&rsquo;re going atomic, go atomic. It&rsquo;ll feel tough in the beginning
but the 1:1 match will be worth it.</p><p>Most importantly though, learn to make these connections in your head. If you can map what you think of in design to what the end engineering build case could be, you&rsquo;ll find that the process of documenting design decisions and handing over projects
become far easier.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>karl@kejk.tech (Karl Koch)</author>
            <enclosure url="https://imgix.cosmicjs.com/d60a4250-b580-11eb-b5b6-fd115d17c053-Thinking-in-design-code2x.png" length="0" type="image/png"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Don’t let your role define you]]></title>
            <link>https://kejk.tech/thoughts/dont-let-your-role-define-you</link>
            <guid>https://kejk.tech/thoughts/dont-let-your-role-define-you</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 May 2021 13:25:33 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[A practical guide on how to navigate your career when the path you're heading down isn't the one you truly want.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This article started off life as an essay on my career. But as I wrote it I realised that as great as that was to me, it&#39;d be more useful for me to provide some key takeaways that you can use in your own career to push to where you want to be. These
are my five key things to remember about your career. What you do doesn&#39;t define you. You can be whoever and whatever you want to be, just keep believing in yourself, and keep pushing down that path one inch at a time.</p><div class="mt-16 pb-16 border-t-2 border-gray-200 dark:border-gray-800"><br></div><h3>Just because you started down one path, it doesn&#39;t mean you can&#39;t change to another&nbsp;</h3><p>I started out in retail sales, moved through to account management, then into technical leadership and now into design. None of this was by accident but it certainly wasn&#39;t planned. I just kept pushing for and pursuing the path I wanted and felt most
comfortable in. You need to do the same. A lot of employers admire people who&#39;ve trodden a unique path because they bring skills others wouldn&#39;t. Be that person.&nbsp;</p><h3>Fight the voice inside that tells you that you&#39;re not worthy&nbsp;</h3><p>There isn&#39;t a day that I don&#39;t experience imposter syndrome. I&#39;m constantly in disbelief that I&#39;m actually a designer somewhere. I&#39;m still convinced I &quot;shouldn&#39;t be allowed&quot; because I followed an unconventional path.
But I am a designer, I do that job and I do it well. It&#39;s hard to fight the negative feelings but you have to remember that you were hired for a reason. You didn&#39;t lie to get there (hopefully), so just keep doing what you do. Someone will tell
you if you&#39;re not up to scratch.&nbsp;</p><h3>Don&#39;t be afraid to learn&nbsp;</h3><p>This one is probably obvious, but seriously, keep learning. I&#39;ve never stopped trying to get to the bottom of things and become better at the core skills I need to deliver my job. But equally, I keep pushing to learn more. Teaching myself SwiftUI
so I can feel closer to engineering&#39;s implementation of our designs, teaching myself Javascript frameworks to be able to build my own personal site and understand the basics of APIs. These are all fundamental to the products we ship, as designers
we should know how they work too. Speak in the same language as your developers, it&#39;ll save you all so much time and build a stronger team. Trust me.&nbsp;</p><h3>Be comfortable with being uncomfortable&nbsp;</h3><p>Get uncomfortable. Push yourself to that point. Then sit there, in it, for a while. Get used to that feeling, it&#39;ll help massively with that voice that tells you you&#39;re not worthy. The more you get used to feeling uncomfortable, the more you&#39;ll be comfortable with it. Psychologists often use <a href="https://www.psychologytools.com/professional/techniques/exposure/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">exposure therapy</a> to help people overcome their fears. Slowly introducing them to the thing that makes them uncomfortable for longer and longer times until they eventually become comfortable. Do that to yourself. Offer to do a Lunch and Learn on a topic to the entire team, take on that Webflow project when you&#39;ve never used it before, offer to man the phones for a couple of hours to deal with customers. Whatever makes you uncomfortable, push yourself to try it, you&#39;ll see it&#39;s not that bad and you&#39;ll grow tenfold because of it.&nbsp;</p><h3>Don&#39;t give up&nbsp;</h3><p>If you&#39;ve not had that flip yet and you&#39;re still in a role you feel defines you even though it&#39;s not the &quot;you&quot; you want to be; don&#39;t give up. Seriously. It can feel like it&#39;s never going to happen. Trust me, I&#39;ve been
there. But if you focus on the earlier steps and commit to that journey, you&#39;ll get there. Seek opportunities in your current business to push into areas you want to be in, even be as bold as to ask your manager if there is any chance. You never
know, that career flip might be right in front of you, you just need the courage to ask.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>karl@kejk.tech (Karl Koch)</author>
            <enclosure url="https://imgix.cosmicjs.com/04668b90-b581-11eb-b5b6-fd115d17c053-Dont-let-your-role-define-you2x.png" length="0" type="image/png"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Code as Design]]></title>
            <link>https://kejk.tech/thoughts/code-as-design</link>
            <guid>https://kejk.tech/thoughts/code-as-design</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 May 2021 13:25:56 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[How development can be learned through a design lens (and how I've managed to do it). ]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3>How development can be learned through a design lens (and how I managed it)</h3><p>I&rsquo;ve said it before, but I am primarily a designer. From an early age I was always drawing and building things, and always asking &ldquo;why?&rdquo;, I&rsquo;m naturally curious I guess. But I&rsquo;ve also explored frontend development from the
early years too.</p><p>I grew up in what I now consider the golden age of the web. I was a pre-teen during the 90&rsquo;s and I got really into modding my Windows 98 and <a href="https://www.instructables.com/Custom-Windows-UI/">XP</a> interfaces to feel custom to my interests at the time (and let&rsquo;s not forget those <a href="https://winampheritage.com/skins">Winamp skins</a>). So I guess, although I wasn&rsquo;t coding at the time, I was beginning to appreciate the link between how the interface <em>looks</em> and how it <em>works</em>.</p><p>In those days, you could do a minimal amount of work to change the appearance, but because you had to install a bunch of different patches and programs to make it work, it did require a reasonable amount of logic and computational literacy to get it working.</p><p>As I got older and things developed online, I got a <a href="www.myspace.com">MySpace</a> account and learnt about the power of HTML and inline styling of CSS. Using &ldquo;View Source&rdquo; I could steal the code other people wrote and modify it to my needs. Again, because I&rsquo;m visual-first, I started with hunting down the mods I liked the look of the most and then modified their code to suit what I liked. Starting with colours, I then worked my way into sizing and, hiding things I didn&rsquo;t like by targeting their <code class=" py-2  language-css">id</code> element and hiding them with <code class=" py-2  language-css"><span class="token property">display</span><span class="token punctuation">:</span> none</code>.</p><p>After MySpace went down the pan&mdash;before Justin Timberlake resurrected it and made it weird&mdash;and things moved on, I drifted away from code and moved more towards the creative side of things. But over the years I was exposed more and more to code through my jobs. And whilst working at <a href="www.cognite.co">Cognite</a> I was fortunate to meet a good friend, <a href="www.nick-wilkins.com">Nick Wilkins</a>, who helped me (and still does) figure a bunch of things out to make me more comfortable with code. More about that here <a href="https://www.kejk.tech/thoughts/designing-in-code">Design as Code</a> .</p><h3>Back to code</h3><p>Since then, I&rsquo;ve been pushing myself to learn more and more about how to implement my design ideas in code. I started by pushing myself to write my <a href="https://kejk.vercel.app">original personal website</a> in pure HTML and CSS. It was clean and simple, but it did the job and refreshed my knowledge. Looking back at it now, it&rsquo;s not that far off where I am now visually, but it&rsquo;s a much more stripped back approach and a far more manual site to update.</p><p>The funny thing is, I didn&rsquo;t design this page first. Contrary to the usual approach, I wanted to leverage something I&rsquo;ve talked about before <a href="https://www.kejk.tech/thoughts/designing-in-code">Development-based Design</a>.</p><blockquote><p>I&rsquo;m not saying you should go away completely from using design tools (I still heavily use Adobe XD and Figma), but I am saying that understanding how to design in code is a superpower that all digital designers should aim to possess.</p></blockquote><p>By manipulating everything in the browser as I went, I learned even more about the power of code, but it felt like something was missing for me. I wanted to find a way to learn the more reactive programming approaches. There&rsquo;d been all this talk about <a href="www.reactjs.org">React</a> and it just seemed like a really good thing for me to push towards. But then I looked at it&hellip;</p><h3>The problem with React and why I picked Vue</h3><p>For me, React just didn&rsquo;t properly click. For developers who understand Javascript it offers really powerful ways to build better, more reactive websites. But as a designer who moved into learning code, it was too hard for me to actually make sense
of. The leap from HTML and CSS to React was massive and it put me off.</p><p>Welcome <a href="https://vuejs.org">Vue</a>! I stumbled across Vue by accident. I knew I wanted to learn something more reactive so I started searching around, found Vue and it just clicked instantly. I dropped the CDN script into a prototype project I was working on at <a href="www.neuerenergy.com">NeuerEnergy</a> and I was away. I could write the HTML and CSS I knew, and then inject some Javascript in&mdash;when I wanted to and had learned to&mdash;to power up the site with clever reactivity.</p><p>So then my love of Vue began and I decided the best way to learn it better was to rebuild my personal website in Vue. So welcome <a href="https://kejk.kejk.now.sh">KEJK v2</a>. I decided that because we&rsquo;d been leveraging the power of Material Design at NeuerEnergy, I wanted to do the same for my personal website (avoiding too much brain overload) and thus found the <a href="https://vuetifyjs.com/en/">Vuetify library</a> to help me on my journey. This meant I could build in the same way I could design, using a design framework that already made sense to me. If I wanted a card, Vuetify had a <code class=" py-2  language-html"><span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;</span>v-card</span><span class="token punctuation">&gt;</span></span></code> to offer me, if I wanted to break into a grid, I had <code class=" py-2  language-html"><span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;</span>v-row</span><span class="token punctuation">&gt;</span></span> and <span class="token tag"><span class="token tag"><span class="token punctuation">&lt;</span>v-col</span><span class="token punctuation">&gt;</span></span></code>to
help me out. It all just made sense.</p><h3>Vue, Nuxt, Cosmic, Drafts and TailwindCSS</h3><p>I loved that personal site, it also provided me with a lot of interest from prospective employers when applying for other design roles. Being able to tell them that I&rsquo;d built the website myself and used Vue to do so gave me a level of skill that other designers weren&rsquo;t always able to offer. This doesn&rsquo;t mean I was <em>better</em> in any way, I just offered <em>different</em> skills and sometimes those skills are super helpful for the right design team.</p><p>I found that exact design team. In my current role at <a href="www.homehero.co.uk">HomeHero</a>, I was hired specifically because I could span the breadth of design and development. Connecting Design and Engineering teams is often an overwhelming and complex task. More often than not, projects aren&rsquo;t handed over properly and a lot of important information is either lost in translation or just straight up missed. Usually, this isn&rsquo;t the fault of anyone particularly, better processes could help (I&rsquo;ll be writing about this at some point soon) but also understanding the language of development and being able to understand <strong>what it takes</strong> to deliver on your grand &ldquo;cross-device isometric animated timeline&rdquo; can have a massive, lasting impact on the connectedness of your team and the quality of the outcome. Moreover, I&rsquo;m able to work directly with the Engineering team to style the frontend of some of our projects, lifting a weight off of them and giving Design the power to own the interface from idea to execution.</p><p>So what was next for me? Well, as you can see there were two iterations of my previous site but you&rsquo;re reading this on the third. I realised that I had an opportunity to improve things. I wanted to make my content more reactive and allow myself more opportunities to utilise a headless CMS to power a lot of the content that could change regularly. This is when I came across <a href="www.cosmicjs.com">CosmicJS</a>. Cosmic is a super flexible, <strong>really well documented</strong> headless CMS (with an unbelievably generous free tier). Cosmic has allowed me to power pages such as my <a href="www.kejk.tech/thoughts">Thoughts</a> (where you&rsquo;re reading this) and <a href="www.kejk.tech/uses">Uses</a>. Now I can update content via Cosmic&rsquo;s
simple backend, avoiding any need to dive into the code to create a new blog post or update my gear.</p><p>Right now, I&rsquo;m writing this on <a href="www.getdrafts.com">Drafts</a> for iPad and will be posting it to my Cosmic bucket using a custom <a href="https://actions.getdrafts.com/a/1fP">POST action</a> I wrote. This makes things frictionless for me now.</p><p>I&rsquo;ve also refactored the site to use <a href="www.nuxtjs.org">Nuxt.js</a> so I can take better advantage of dynamic page routing, SEO meta info and their module system. I even went as far as to ditch my use of Material Design and refactored all of the HTML to use <a href="www.tailwindcss.com">TailwindCSS</a>. This means I&rsquo;m looking up docs less and focusing on writing code in a way my brain already thinks&hellip; in CSS.</p><h3>So what&rsquo;s the future?</h3><p>I&rsquo;m not really sure where I go next with things. I can probably better implement Cosmic into my site, making more content dynamic. I also want to write some more Drafts actions to try and make things like updating a post more straightforward. But
other than that, I&rsquo;m feeling really excited about where things are and what I&rsquo;ve managed to teach myself.</p><p>I&rsquo;ve said it before several times, but I urge you if you&rsquo;re a designer who&rsquo;s working with developers; learn the basics of HTML, CSS and Javascript, try out a framework like Vue + Nuxt (give SwiftUI a try too). They&rsquo;re all becoming
so much more accessible to people without programming knowledge already (or a more visually-focused brain like me) and I promise it&rsquo;ll be worth it.</p><p>If I can do it, so can you.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>karl@kejk.tech (Karl Koch)</author>
            <enclosure url="https://imgix.cosmicjs.com/0f334900-b581-11eb-b5b6-fd115d17c053-Code-as-Design2x.png" length="0" type="image/png"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Designing in the open]]></title>
            <link>https://kejk.tech/thoughts/designing-in-the-open</link>
            <guid>https://kejk.tech/thoughts/designing-in-the-open</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 May 2021 13:26:18 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[What I’ve learnt about sharing constantly and live designing with my team.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3>What I&rsquo;ve learnt about sharing constantly and live designing with my team</h3><p>Designers are precious people. Arguably, the vast majority of Creatives are precious people. From my own personal experience, observing teammates and generally speaking to other creatives, it&rsquo;s apparent that we seek perfection and are often uncomfortable
with sharing works in progress.</p><p>If you work in design, you&rsquo;ll be familiar with the WIP abbreviation. You might have used it in file extensions <code class="  language-text">`homepage_redesign-WIP.fig`</code> or within the document itself <code class="  language-text">`homepage_newScreens-WIP`</code>or you may go as far as using more blunt language to try and stop prying eyes <code class="  language-text">`homepage_newScreens-NotReadyYet-DO_NOT_TOUCH`</code>.</p><p>When I moved to HomeHero, I was one of two designers. The very nature of having two individuals meant that we were somewhat forced into working in the open. We, in most cases, would be working across the same files because of the needs of the organisation
at the time.</p><p>One thing we did though, was use Figma. By default, Figma&rsquo;s goal is to enable and encourage working out in the open. Whether that&rsquo;s through the cross-platform, web-based tool&rsquo;s easy sharing options, or the multi-cursor features, it became
super easy for us to bring product managers and developers into the fold too.&nbsp;</p><p>As we&rsquo;ve grown, we&rsquo;ve ensured that we maintain this approach to working. Although we only open access to our files once they&rsquo;re in the right shape, we actively seek product manager and developer input during the early stages of design.
Allowing them in to the fold when the file is still a mess of ideas and mistakes ensures that we don&rsquo;t spend too long going down the wrong path or thinking we&rsquo;ve understood the brief but we&rsquo;ve actually got it hugely wrong.</p><h3>Being consistent</h3><p>This is all well and good, but it&rsquo;s easy to lose consistency with this and retreat back to the WIP-obsessed designer mindset.&nbsp;</p><p>We&rsquo;ve done it as a team. We started with really open access in Figma. Anyone with a HomeHero email address could just jump in to any file and have a nose around and have their say. We experienced a few moments where we got some unhelpful feedback
on parts of a project that were just experiments. And the problem is, no matter what the page was labelled or what text is included on the page, it&rsquo;s not always clear to an outsider that something is an experiment.</p><p>It&rsquo;s not an issue just for us as designers. Receiving unnecessary feedback isn&rsquo;t helpful, and it&rsquo;s also a huge waste of time for the person who spent their precious hours adding comments to something that was a passing idea anyway.</p><h3>Finding a happy medium</h3><p>In order to maintain our openness across the organisation, whilst also ensuring we don&rsquo;t fall into the old traps, we&rsquo;ve spent some time crafting a way forwards.</p><h4>Our default position is that only Design have Figma access to our Team now.</h4><p>This means that only the design team have open access across all the Figma documents we&rsquo;ve created. This allows us to be working out in the open within the confines of the Design Team. It stops us from keeping our ideas just to ourselves, obsessing
over them until they&rsquo;re &ldquo;perfect&rdquo;, but it also ensures we don&rsquo;t end up in the land of unnecessary comments.</p><h4>We add the relevant PM, Developer and and others to a singular, specific file.</h4><p>By only adding the right people to the right file at the right time, we guarantee that we&rsquo;ve put the file into the right kind of state to receive the feedback we need, but without resorting to &nbsp;<code class="  language-text">`homepage_redesign-final_FINAL.fig`</code>.</p><h4>We design together, live.</h4><p>The main thing we spend a lot of time doing now&mdash;beyond collaborating inside the same design files&mdash;is actually designing whilst sharing our screen.&nbsp;</p><p>If we&rsquo;re working through a specific problem, we&rsquo;ve found that screen sharing-based design sessions work great. In some ways we&rsquo;re trying to mimick the idea of being able to do in-person peer-designing or whiteboard sessions, but we&rsquo;ve
found that it really increases our ability to take an idea from experimentation through to a more defined execution.&nbsp;</p><p>Oftentimes, one of the team will share their screen whilst designing and we&rsquo;ll all jump into the file too. This means that we can let one person essentially lead the design process whilst still dropping in and adding things we think of in the moment.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>karl@kejk.tech (Karl Koch)</author>
            <enclosure url="https://imgix.cosmicjs.com/1ea17b00-b581-11eb-b5b6-fd115d17c053-Designing-in-the-open2x.png" length="0" type="image/png"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[From problem to plugin]]></title>
            <link>https://kejk.tech/thoughts/from-problem-to-plugin</link>
            <guid>https://kejk.tech/thoughts/from-problem-to-plugin</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 May 2021 13:26:48 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Learning Typescript, the Figma API and solving a real personal problem.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3>Background&nbsp;</h3><p>As I&#39;ve mentioned before, I&#39;ve long had a passion for learning new skills and that&#39;s especially true when it comes to picking up new frontend development skills.&nbsp;</p><p>When I started learning <a href="https://www.vuejs.org/" target="_blank">Vue</a>, I chose to utilise the <a href="https://www.vuetifyjs.com/" target="_blank">Vuetify</a> library to speed up the process and allow me to focus less on creating CSS and more on learning the necessary JavaScript and language specifics. Using the Vuetify library taught me the basics of working with APIs to leverage specific behaviour.&nbsp;</p><p>When I moved over to using <a href="https://www.figma.com/" target="_blank">Figma</a> as my main design tool outside of my day job, I wanted to find ways to make the process of handing over to development easier. Although Figma does a great job of handling <a href="https://www.figma.com/best-practices/guide-to-developer-handoff/" target="_blank">developer handoff</a>, it renders the font sizes as pixels much like any other design tool does.&nbsp;</p><h3>The solution&nbsp;</h3><p>I was desperate to have an easier way to provide the relevant Rem or Em values to developers (including myself) so that I didn&#39;t have to find an online converter or just make up random values to try and find the closest match. And that&#39;s how <a href="https://www.figma.com/community/plugin/837070613195594890/Px-%E2%80%BA%E2%80%BA-Em" target="_blank">Px &rsaquo;&rsaquo; Em</a> was born.&nbsp;</p><p>Over one evening, I was able to dig into the <a href="https://www.figma.com/plugin-docs/api/api-overview" target="_blank">Figma API documentation</a>, make sense of what was possible and create a basic proof of concept that did what I needed it to do.&nbsp;</p><h3>The final output&nbsp;</h3><p>Over the course of the following few days, I made adjustments and updates to the plugin, enabling some extra functionality for changing the base Px value from the browser default of 16px and also allowing for the conversion ratio to be changed based on
some common scales (including the Golden Ratio).&nbsp;</p><h4>The core Px &rsaquo;&rsaquo; Em functionality is:</h4><ul class="list-disc ml-8"><li>Open the plugin without selections to convert any number to ems</li><li>Select a text node anywhere in your files and open the plugin to see the current pixel value and convert it to ems</li><li>Change the current selection to update the input value and enable a new conversion</li><li>Change the baseline px value to whatever you want it to be and see the relevant changes in em conversion</li><li>Change the scale by which you want to convert based on common scales used</li></ul><p>Creating the code wasn&#39;t as complex as first anticipated, so here&#39;s a snippet of how the actual calculation works as a function.</p><div class="w-3/4 overflow-x-auto whitespace-pre-wrap"><pre class=" rounded-xl  language-javascript"><code class="  language-javascript"><span class="token keyword">function</span> <span class="token function">pxToEms</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>px<span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">{</span></code>
<code class="  language-javascript"> <span class="token keyword">var</span> baseValue <span class="token operator">=</span> </code>
<code class="  language-javascript">  </code><code class="  language-javascript">document</code>
<code class="  language-javascript">   <span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">getElementById</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token string">&#39;newPx&#39;</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span></code>
<code class="  language-javascript">   <span class="token punctuation">.</span>value<span class="token punctuation">;</span></code>
<code class="  language-javascript"> <span class="token keyword">var</span> scale <span class="token operator">=</span> </code>
<code class="  language-javascript">  </code><code class="  language-javascript">document</code>
<code class="  language-javascript">   <span class="token punctuation">.</span><span class="token function">getElementById</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token string">&#39;scale&#39;</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span></code>
<code class="  language-javascript">   <span class="token punctuation">.</span>value<span class="token punctuation">;</span></code>
<code class="  language-javascript"> <span class="token keyword">function</span> <span class="token function">calculate</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span><span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token punctuation">{</span></code>
<code class="  language-javascript"> <span class="token keyword">return</span><span class="token punctuation">(</span>px <span class="token operator">/</span> baseValue<span class="token punctuation">)</span><span class="token operator">*</span> scale<span class="token punctuation">;</span></code>
<code class="  language-javascript"> <span class="token punctuation">}</span></code>
<code class="  language-javascript"> <span class="token keyword">return</span> calculate<span class="token punctuation">;</span></code>
<code class="  language-javascript"><span class="token punctuation">}</span></code></pre></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>karl@kejk.tech (Karl Koch)</author>
            <enclosure url="https://imgix.cosmicjs.com/2d2992c0-b581-11eb-b5b6-fd115d17c053-From-problem-to-plugin2x.png" length="0" type="image/png"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Ten Principles for Good Design]]></title>
            <link>https://kejk.tech/thoughts/ten-principles-for-good-design</link>
            <guid>https://kejk.tech/thoughts/ten-principles-for-good-design</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 May 2021 13:27:07 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[I decided to put together a free, multi-device, minimal wallpaper of Ram's ten principles. ]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3>A free minimal wallpaper of Ram&#39;s ten principles.&nbsp;</h3><p>I&#39;ve long been a huge fan of Dieter Rams and his extensive portfolio of work at Braun and Vits&oelig;.</p><p>When I heard that Gary Hustwit was looking for funding to film a movie about Rams&#39; career, I couldn&#39;t resist backing it on <a href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/1019019367/rams-the-first-feature-documentary-about-dieter-ra" target="_blank">Kickstarter.</a></p><p>One of the perks was to get a letterpress of the ten principles on card. This was set in a beautiful font close to <a href="http://atipofoundry.com/fonts/archia" rel="noreferrer" target="_blank">Archia</a> by Atipo (I believe it might be <a href="https://fonts.google.com/specimen/Space+Mono?query=space+m" rel="noreferrer" target="_blank">Space Mono</a> by Colophon) that I wanted to reimagine for the digital screen as a reminder of the principles. This allowed me to have a constant reminder to ensure my designs are always refined and focus on delivering maximum value in a minimal form.&nbsp;</p><p>I&#39;ve made this wallpaper available to download in three sizes for mobile, tablet and desktop. You can grab them below. In my version, I&#39;ve set this in Archia.</p><p><a href="https://res.cloudinary.com/kejk/image/upload/v1590345853/Desktop_bwwsio.png" target="_blank"><img src="https://res.cloudinary.com/kejk/image/upload/v1590345853/Desktop_bwwsio.png" class="rounded-xl fr-fic fr-dii" style="max-width: 900px; width: 100%;"></a></p><div class="flex flex-row justify-center"><a href="https://res.cloudinary.com/kejk/raw/upload/v1590345921/Rams_Ten_Principles_Wallpapers_god3jk.zip"><button class="text-black bg-gray-50 hover:bg-gray-100 dark:hover:bg-gray-800 dark:text-white dark:bg-gray-900 transition ease-in-out 200 rounded-xl px-6 py-3 btn btn--primary">Download all</button></a></div>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>karl@kejk.tech (Karl Koch)</author>
            <enclosure url="https://imgix.cosmicjs.com/3c812f80-b581-11eb-b5b6-fd115d17c053-Ten-Principles-for-Good-Design2x.png" length="0" type="image/png"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Design as Code]]></title>
            <link>https://kejk.tech/thoughts/designing-in-code</link>
            <guid>https://kejk.tech/thoughts/designing-in-code</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 May 2021 13:27:29 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[What learning Vue has taught me about the future of design, development and the modern web.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3>What learning Vue has taught me about the future of design.&nbsp;</h3><p>So let&#39;s start with some background; I&#39;ve been tinkering with website code since the early 2000s when MySpace was first on the scene and I was trying to customise the look of my personal MySpace page.</p><p>At that time, it involved a hell of a lot of inline styling and hacking around to find out what would work and what wouldn&#39;t. Thanks to the beauty of &#39;View Source&#39;, it was possible to see the detail of what another person had done, pull that
code, and tweak to your heart&#39;s content until you broke it again.</p><p>After MySpace died and I moved on to other, less emo, things I found myself falling away from programming. That was until I started a job in healthcare leading the digital design and development of projects. This all came about organically but I was kinda
out of my depth.</p><p>Luckily, I had a great relationship with the core developer on our team and over time started to tinker again, this time though, in production code (mostly because I did the crappy little jobs that he liked not having to do).</p><p>What I started to learn, was the magic of development-based design, or frontend design, where I would manipulate the UI (or DOM) inside the browser itself to see how I preferred things. It felt like the old days of tinkering on MySpace again.</p><p>The more I did it, the more I enjoyed the experience of designing in the browser. I&#39;m not saying you should go away completely from using design tools (I still heavily use <a class="text-indigo-600 dark:text-indigo-300 font-medium" href="https://adobe.com/xd" target="_blank">Adobe XD</a> and <a class="text-indigo-600 dark:text-indigo-300 font-medium" href="http://figma.com/" target="_blank">Figma</a>), but I am saying that understanding how to design in code is a superpower that all digital designers should
aim to possess.&nbsp;</p><p>Here are the key reasons why:</p><ol class="list-decimal ml-8"><li>You can see the direct effect of a decision, in the browser, in real-time</li><li>You can learn the language of development, allowing for better cross-communication between you and your development team</li><li>You can increase your output at your company, enabling developers to focus on the logic and complexities whilst you manipulate the styling in production code</li><li>You can improve your ability to work independently on client projects as a freelancer</li></ol><p>The idea of the Frontend Designer <a class="text-indigo-600 dark:text-indigo-300 font-medium" href="https://bradfrost.com/blog/post/frontend-design/" target="_blank">isn&#39;t new</a> but it certainly isn&#39;t widespread either. I strongly believe that this hybrid role is the future of design and, with the flexibility of <a class="text-indigo-600 dark:text-indigo-300 font-medium" href="https://www.webcomponents.org/" target="_blank">Web Components</a> and powerful frameworks like Vue, React and Angular enabling better component-driven design, Designers understanding code is going to be more important than ever.&nbsp;</p><p>If you&#39;re looking to evolve beyond HTML and CSS as a designer, but find JavaScript scary as hell (like I did) then check out <a class="text-indigo-600 dark:text-indigo-300 font-medium" href="https://vuejs.org/" target="_blank">Vue</a> and follow their extremely powerful and easy to follow documentation.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>karl@kejk.tech (Karl Koch)</author>
            <enclosure url="https://imgix.cosmicjs.com/4897ab00-b581-11eb-b5b6-fd115d17c053-Design-as-Code2x.png" length="0" type="image/png"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Getting to yes]]></title>
            <link>https://kejk.tech/thoughts/getting-to-yes</link>
            <guid>https://kejk.tech/thoughts/getting-to-yes</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 May 2021 13:27:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Why I think designers and developers should learn the basics of sales. ]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3>Why designers and developers should learn the basics of sales.</h3><p>It&rsquo;s easy to think that as a designer or developer, you&rsquo;re responsible for the functionality, usability or appearance of the product you&rsquo;re working on. This applies across product design, web design, architecture and even the original
meaning of product design (physical product production).</p><p>That is true, that is your core responsibility, but what happens when you go over-the-line with the product, when the product is finally ready for your sales team&mdash;if you have one&mdash;to go out and sell?</p><p>If the answer is &ldquo;I don&rsquo;t know&rdquo; then there&rsquo;s a serious organisational disconnect and you&rsquo;re doing yourselves a disservice. You worked for months slaving over the minute details, unit testing until you&rsquo;re blue in the face, hunting down that broken <em>for loop</em> deep inside a component file; and yet, once that&rsquo;s over you throw it over the fence to sales and start working on the next feature set.&nbsp;</p><p>But how do your team sell what you&rsquo;re working on? What are the things that they say to hook potential or existing customers? And why does this matter?</p><p>First, let&rsquo;s start with a story. Early on in my career, I was a sales person. I left University with a Masters in Fine Art but didn&rsquo;t feel I was worthy of a design or development role (despite developing skills in both places for around 10
years prior) so I went from my full-time retail job at Apple to working as an Account Executive in pharmaceutical advertising. My job was to keep projects on track, win new business and keep clients happy. I was solely responsible for selling the vision
of our design and development teams and ensure coordination and clarification across the board.</p><p>When it came to meetings, I had to work hard to explain how something had been done, why it would take 2 months to build &ldquo;that&rdquo; feature and why they couldn&rsquo;t have the &ldquo;other&rdquo; feature they wanted. Throughout that process,
I learnt the intricacies and nuances of behaviour, of the complexity of communicating something widely understood by designers and developers, but deeply misunderstood by customers. I expanded skills learnt from Apple Retail about how to explain the complex
in a simple way, breaking technology down to its simplest form and developing similes and metaphors for different approaches. All of this led to accurate communication and valuable insight into the customer experience.</p><p>So, fast forward to now. Now I design and develop the frontend experience of products. From initial idea through to final execution. Throughout this process, I have regular touch points with our sales team to ensure that each feature is developed deeply
inline with the requirements of our target market and explain why we&rsquo;ve designed it one way, or developed it another. Why it can&rsquo;t be exactly like that thing they showed me that one time that kind of did the same thing. Why it&rsquo;s going
to take six months to develop that special graph that takes data from 56 sources, runs a machine learning algorithm to extract the most valuable insights, feeds it back into the UI and generates a personalised graph in real-time with up-to-the-second
data.</p><p>But I also go to those meetings, sit in on those calls, talk to those potential customers and explain these things myself. Explain our UI decisions in detail. Spend hours in workshops justifying decisions and ensuring our customers see why. And in these
workshops, our sales team learn. They learn how we think about design and development decisions, why we push back when we do, and how to communicate this to customers. They learn to not promise the earth and that it&rsquo;ll be delivered in 2 weeks. They
learn to speak in a language that is both technical and customer-centric.</p><p>What happens, is both sides learn how to communicate better. With each other, with the customer, with their peers. Designers and developers learn how to sell. Sales people learn how to communicate technological ideas and not over promise.</p><p>Everyone wins.</p><p>Ultimately, by tightly coupling sales with the technology teams, the result is a wonderful world where all parties are working to the same goal and with the same attitudes, understanding and beliefs.</p><p><strong>The</strong> team must be <strong>one</strong> team. It&rsquo;s the only way it&rsquo;ll ever work.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>karl@kejk.tech (Karl Koch)</author>
            <enclosure url="https://imgix.cosmicjs.com/53e77b20-b581-11eb-b5b6-fd115d17c053-Getting-to-yes2x.png" length="0" type="image/png"/>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why ‘users’ are humans]]></title>
            <link>https://kejk.tech/thoughts/why-users-are-humans</link>
            <guid>https://kejk.tech/thoughts/why-users-are-humans</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 May 2021 13:28:06 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Design is about people, and I've been thinking a lot about the problem of the term 'user'.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3>Design is about people.</h3><p>Working in the healthcare sector, it&rsquo;s sometimes hard to forget those people that you affect the most through the work you do. It can be right there in front of you, seeing children living longer lives because of the work you and the healthcare
company you support do. But it&rsquo;s also sometimes easy to think about those end individuals as &lsquo;users&rsquo;.</p><p>User Experience is a hot topic and has been for some time. Really, it was birthed in Silicon Valley as a way of thinking about the end person using your product and avoid a narrow focus on delivering a solution that you (as in the company) think is the
right thing. The problem with a user focus is that it&rsquo;s easy to abstract the term user into being a statistic. A user is a term we attribute onto a person that uses our product, but it is far too easy for that to become a percentage on a spreadsheet
or a cumulative number that appears on an analytics report. Treating the people we affect most as users can have a negative effect on how we think about our products and lead us to believe that our focus is on increasing that percentage or building up
those numbers, only.</p><h4>Why we should be Human-centred</h4><p>Human-centered design is a term that&#39;s been explored and advocated for by many established designers from David and Tom Kelley, to Donald Norman and even into architecture by way of Mike Cooley.</p><p>My argument is for a permanant change, a move away from user-centricity and user experience and towards human-centricity and human-experience. By doing this, we can&rsquo;t abstract away who we are affecting. Those directly effected are other humans and
as such, it helps focus the mind on doing our best work and allows to think more wholly about what we&rsquo;re creating.</p><p>Numbers are important, we need to keep an eye on those analytics reports and the statistics from audience feedback, but that needn&rsquo;t draw away from the very humans that we are affecting. Sometimes, decisions that may seem bad statistically, are
actually right ethically. Making decisions that directly impact on the humans using your product are often some of the hardest and most important. Losing sight of those real people that you&rsquo;re affecting with every slight change of pixels on a UI,
removal of &lsquo;old&rsquo; functionality or choice of distribution platform, can have lasting effects on their respect for your company and the values you represent.</p><p>So think carefully about every decision you make as a brand and contemplate the impact on the humans you&rsquo;re working for, because no matter what you believe, the other humans of this earth are the people you&rsquo;re helping and those humans need
you to care about them first. You work for them, whether it feels like it or not.</p><p>Humans are not users, users are humans.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>karl@kejk.tech (Karl Koch)</author>
            <enclosure url="https://imgix.cosmicjs.com/5ff62e70-b581-11eb-b5b6-fd115d17c053-Why-users-are-humans2x.png" length="0" type="image/png"/>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>